<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Baroness Nuala O&#39;Loan DBE MRIA</title>
    <description>The official website of Baroness Nuala O&#39;Loan DBE MRIA</description>
    <link>http://nualaoloan.com//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://nualaoloan.com//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 16:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Dec 2015 16:43:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building the Peace - Getting the Foundations Right</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon.  It is very good to be here with you to participate in the celebration of the 50th anniversary of the founding of Corrymeela. This property where you now sit was purchased by the Rev Ray Davey and his QUB students for £7,000 in early 1965. That money, which was a mighty sum in those days, about ten times the annual salary, was raised within 10 days: testament to the courage and determination of those involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read that Corrymeela has three possible meanings: “Hill of Harmony,” “Hill of Honeysuckle,” and “Lumpy Crossroads.”  Hill of Harmony is attractive but my guess is that Corrymeela has seen much more than harmony in those 50 years, constructive though that may have been. Honeysuckle is lovely but I didn’t see any on the way up.  Lumpy Crossroads is probably the most appealing, suggestive as it is of the pot holes, the bad corners, the  diminished visibility and comprehension which have been so much part of our journey.   There is a suggestion of humour too!  I like that.  I am sure that Corrymeela  has seen many moments of fun and laughter over those five decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;respite from the violence of those days: the holidays, weekends, summer breaks, camps which were so much part of life here at the time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to Northern Ireland in 1976, when times were pretty bad and  I fairly quickly became aware of Corrymeela, firstly in terms of what I understood as respite from the violence of those days: the holidays, weekends, summer breaks, camps which were so much part of life here at the time. So many of you know so much more than I do about those days, about this place you describe as one of gathering, work, faith and discussion; about the bringing together of people of different backgrounds, different political and religious beliefs and different identities together, about the occasionally bewildered parents and children who came to this rugged North Antrim coast, which can seem so wild and inhospitable and grey, but which  became a place of refuge, respite, reconciliation and relaxation for thousands of people.   The work which has been done here has been both personal and communal.  It has taken so many forms,  individual, community based, sector based, cross community, economic, developmental, and a huge contribution has been made here to the evolution of peace in our troubled country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, 50 years later, you have almost 40 full time staff, you have 20 year–long volunteers and interns, and hundreds of other shorter term volunteers. Many of you have been working on the site for decades, giving so generously of your time and energy to others service to the work. I would like to pay tribute to all who have worked here, and to remember all those whose work here on earth is done, but most particularly to remember the faith and determination of Ray Davey and of his gentle and courageous wife Kathleen.  And since this is place founded on Christianity, I give thanks to the Lord for the generosity, the compassion, the humour, the energy and the love that has made it all possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-we-were&quot;&gt;Where we were&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can seem almost unreal now when we see on documentaries the old film footage of the years of the Troubles.  I spoke recently in Ballycastle about a book I launched a book last year by Eimear O’Callaghan, Belfast Days - a 1972 Teenage Diary.  It recounts graphically the reality of life in those dark and difficult days, all intertwined with the normal preoccupations of a young girl growing up with her friends and family.  It is very challenging to read the story of our past, to watch the film footage of those early days, to remember those awful nights when Belfast was subjected to multiple bomb threats and attacks, when without sat nav, and often without street maps, we tried to find our way through the diversions to home, being able to take only one road and ending up often in alien territory, recognisable as alien by the painted kerb stones, the flags and the murals which were so much part of our culture!  it didn’t matter whether one was a Christian Catholic or a Christian Protestant, one knew that the reality was that one was in territory where one would be better not to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;we tried to find our way through the diversions to home, being able to take only one road&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember too the students who used to come and tell me of being picked up by the soldiers patrolling the streets at night and driven to the others’ territory sometimes beaten up and thrown out of the land rovers to make their lonely frightened way home. I remember the bombs exploding across Belfast Lough as I lectured in Jordanstown, and sometimes even exploding on the university campus. In some ways it does not seem possible that what happened with all its terror, tragedy, trauma, destruction and division could have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the bad years some 116 people died in the Republic of Ireland. There were over 3600 terrorist related murders in Northern Ireland and  some 50,000 injuries as a consequence of the security situation here over the thirty eight years. The Victims Commission estimated that the conflict resulted in 500,000 ‘victims’ in Northern Ireland. It defines ‘victims’ as those who are directly affected by ‘bereavement’, ‘physical injury’ or ‘trauma’ as a result of the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-present-reality&quot;&gt;Our present reality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now children play once more in summer, and rioting is not the inevitable occurrence which they must face.  We do not see soldiers on our streets. But we still have paramilitary violence and we still have too much sectarianism. In the year ending 31 March 2015 PSNI statistics show that there were 3 deaths due to the security situation, 94 shootings and assaults by paramilitaries of which 48 were by loyalists and 46 by republicans.  There were 73 shooting incidents and 26 bombing incidents. 58 firearms were recovered, 22.94 kgs of explosives and 4,569  rounds of explosives were recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has been achieved. We have had ceasefires, disarmament, decommissioning, prisoner release, the establishment of the NI Assembly, the devolution of legislative power to that Assembly, most recently the devolution of power over matters of justice and policing, though it is not complete devolution. The UK has retained its control over matters affecting its national security. The past keeps coming up though. That is normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Different solutions have been found across the world to deal with different elements of the problem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it is normal too that after such conflict there will be a debate, whether acknowledged or unacknowledged, about the legacy of the past, about its capacity to undo the present, and about the cost, both of addressing past injustice, and of failing so to do.  Northern Ireland is no different from other conflicts in this respect. Different solutions have been found across the world to deal with different elements of the problem - truth commissions, various forms of reparation, resettlement of displaced people, reintegration of participants into society, disarmament and decommissioning.  The models are there.  So why is dealing with the past such a difficult issue for Northern Ireland?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-solutions&quot;&gt;Our solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we need to do?  The answers are fairly simple and we have identified them as a people, most recently in the Stormont House Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-solutions-include&quot;&gt;The solutions include:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Commission on Flags, Identity, Culture and Tradition which was to be established by June 2015 to report within 18 months of its being established,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Powers to take responsibility for parades and related protests should, in principle, be devolved to the NI Assembly,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By 2016 there will be an Oral History Archive,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A research project as part of the Archive, led by academics to produce a factual historical timeline and statistical analysis of the Troubles,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Victims and Survivors will have access to high quality services, respecting the principles of choice and need a comprehensive Mental Trauma Service will be implemented,
work will be undertaken to seek an acceptable way forward on the proposal for a pension for severely physically injured victims in Northern Ireland,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An Historical Investigations Unit (HIU) to take forward outstanding cases from the HET process, and the legacy work of the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland (PONI). A report will be produced in each case. The HIU should aim to complete its work within five years of its establishment,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There will be an Independent Commission on Information Retrieval (ICIR), building on the precedent provided by the Independent Commission on the Location of Victims’ Remains. The objective of the ICIR will be to enable victims and survivors to seek and privately receive information about the (Troubles- related) deaths of their next of kin,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An Implementation and Reconciliation Group (IRG) will be established to oversee themes, archives and information recovery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A compact civic advisory panel which would meet regularly to consider key social, cultural and economic issues and to advise the NI Executive,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The UK Government and the Irish Government endorse the need for respect for and recognition of the Irish language in Northern Ireland.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How could those two issues have been so tied up in one agreement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all fine words; given effect they would go a long way to consolidating our peace.  The problem is that our governments seems incapable of delivering on what they have agreed.  These vital elements, and the funding for them, upon which we will work to consolidate the peace which we have, will only be delivered if there is agreement on welfare reform.  How could those two issues have been so tied up in one agreement that failure to deliver on welfare reform dictates inability to deliver on dealing with the past.  Where is the morality in that situation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are told by our political commentators that this is a difficult time for us, and the our hard won institutions are at risk. But Northern Ireland seems to be always in crisis. There is no good time to do things in Northern Ireland. We have lurched from crisis to crisis in the context of the Troubles, buttressed on occasion by governmental help of the fiscal kind, by time, diplomatic effort and lots of other support - British, Irish and American, and also by the trading of legislative change, bringing, for example, equality and a degree of impunity for wrongdoing in exchange for decommissioning, for ceasefires and for peace. Thus is peace made. It is not an easy business; it inevitably requires compromise by all parties; it takes time; it can break down. We know from the work of peacemaking across the world, that most peace agreements break down within 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that it is all the more imperative that governments and people act now to ensure our peace. It is seventeen years since the GFA, our governments have legal and moral responsibilities and are not delivering on those responsibilities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow our Governments and we as a society, have to find within ourselves the capacity and the willingness to build our peace.  Knowing what we need to do we must find the way forward together because people are still suffering the aftermath of the Troubles on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ongoing-problems&quot;&gt;Ongoing problems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are massive inadequacies in providing services on the ground to victims.  We have 91 victims organisations, a Victims and Survivors Service, a publicly funded Victims and Survivors Forum, and at last a new Victims’ Commissioner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time to provide properly for those 500,000 ‘victims’ - those directly affected by ‘bereavement’, ‘physical injury’ or ‘trauma’ as a result of the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We currently have survivors of Troubles related attacks who must choose between pain relief services and physiotherapy, we have Troubles related amputees who wait months for prosthetic limbs with all the attendant problems which that creates. Afghanistan, France, Greece, Italy, Israel, and Spain provide dedicated pension entitlement to individuals injured in acts of terrorism or internal conflict. NI Troubles victims do not get any pension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The consequences of conflict related violence are trans-generational and often people affected experience a need for counselling long after the event&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have some excellent good practice here, but it is under massive pressure.  Demand for counselling sessions at WAVE, the biggest victims’ organisation here, rose 52% last year, with applicants aged from 6 to the late 80s. The consequences of conflict related violence are trans-generational and often people affected experience a need for counselling long after the event which gave rise to the trauma.  In so many cases the impact is so great at the time of the trauma and for decades afterwards, that people fear the risk of reliving that trauma in counselling so much that, even though the trauma may be destroying them, they fear even more the counselling process.  Yet so much can be achieved through counselling and other therapies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not invest sufficiently in the care of our victims. The total amount of funding granted by the Victims and Survivors Service in Northern Ireland to help all those bereaved, wounded, traumatised by the Troubles for the two years from 2013-2015 is £12,377,512.  And the money which is available is fragmented across organisations, and we have to ask whether we are using the money which is available to best effect, when in so many serious cases  we can’t provide necessary basic therapies and treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A PSNI freedom of information request showed that in 2013 we spent almost £23m policing parades and protests in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent £12m between July 2013 and last October 2014, on the Twaddell Avenue protests, almost the same sum as we have to spend on all our victims over the two year period from 2013 -2015!   In June this year the Justice Minister said it is costing £333,000  a month.  At a time when we do not have enough money to provide essentials such as counselling, physiotherapy and prosthetic limbs,   we continue to haemorrhage money into a situation which is exacerbating the existing tensions in North Belfast.  And Twaddell Avenue is all just one small part of a legacy of the past with which we are not dealing.  Leadership on a massive scale is required in both communities to resolve this issue and to allow this money to be used for the good of all our people, not wasted as it is currently being wasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of years, we have seen conflict between the Police and the Police Ombudsman, only resolved when the Police Ombudsman brought the Chief Constable to court, problems between the Coroners and the PSNI, massive problems with PSNI’s HET, now abolished, a Chief Constable who has said that he does not have the resources to deal with the past, if he is to police the present, a coronial system which is on its knees with only two Coroners currently in office, one of whom is retiring in October.  Our criminal justice system which is supposed to help deliver the Rule of Law is not working properly, and recognition of and support for the Rule of Law must be one of the foundations stones upon which we build the peace. We need more leadership in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-trust&quot;&gt;Building trust&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, although so much has been done, much remains to be done. This work of peace making can only be incremental  and it can be very difficult. What then are the foundations upon we can all work to create that solid sustainable peace for which so many have yearned for so long. I believe that trust is the key to all relationships, and that trust is the product of both knowledge and understanding – when people know the other and understand the other, they see the other no longer as the other but rather as another person who shares their world.  When the person shares their world they cease to be such a threat. Part of our problem must be that we still do not, as a society, understand that our Catholicism and our Protestantism should bring us to trust one another as brothers and sisters in Christ, for that is what we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;truth-and-reconciliation&quot;&gt;Truth and reconciliation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truth and reconciliation are the foundations upon which trust can grow, and from trust can emerge a society which is truly democratic, in which the rule of law exists and is respected and real, in which there is peace.  Real trust is usually the product of knowledge and understanding and relationship. This has been such a large part of the work of Corrymeela.  When people know what has happened and why, when they experience a relationship based on respect and love, they can understand, and when they understand they can make a decision as to whether to trust again.  Those who have been most seriously hurt will need time and space and reparation, whether by apology and acknowledgement of what has happened, or by the provision of resources – compensation, counselling etc.  The complexity of our current situation requires many different initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suffering and difficulties of the last years in Northern Ireland are well known, though I think that to some degree we are being encouraged to forget and to “get on with life” when actually we need to acknowledge the unhealed pain and grief, and find ways, be it story telling, art, crafts, listening, memorials or investigation to bring some resolution and some healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;there is also a fear that such trust as we have grown, such reconciliation as we have achieved might be undermined if we move forward&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it seems to me that at governmental levels there is also a fear that such trust as we have grown, such reconciliation as we have achieved might be undermined if we move forward in this process of establishing the truth. There is a tension between the fear of the consequences of revealing the truth, and the needs of the families of those who died, and of society as a whole, which is at the heart of today’s debates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflict, on the scale on which we experienced it is always very messy. And so there are fears, expectations even, that what might emerge from some form of truth telling process, be it through investigation or through hearings such as those conducted by the South African Truth Commission, will be damaging, will contradict the received wisdom in each of the communities, will not be ‘the whole truth.” In the case of South Africa where 7116 people applied for amnesty in return for telling their story, only 1176 got their amnesty, even among those cases it is said that there were people who having been granted amnesty did not tell the whole story. 
 In Northern Ireland there are difficult conversations to be had, difficult acknowledgements to be made about wrongdoing by state and non state actors, reparations to be made for injuries suffered, and ultimately acceptance of the realities about which people still hesitate to speak, but which are manifest in cases like Bloody Sunday, in the recovery of the bodies of the Disappeared, stolen from their families, savagely murdered and secretly buried. It must happen if we are to be reconciled as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the question must surely be, “Can we afford not to?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as we look towards truth and reconciliation as the foundations for peace, there are those who are asking whether we can afford truth if we seek reconciliation; whether reconciliation which is not based on truth is truly reconciliation, or merely a papering over the cracks. If we cannot face the truth, can we secure that reconciliation which must be the basis of a sustainable peace? As we look at the history of our country, as we contemplate the pain and suffering of the bereaved of the Troubles, the agony of the families of the Disappeared, the ongoing activities of both republican and loyalist paramilitaries, and their effect on our capacity to function as a people, to attract inward investment and to consolidate the peace, the question must surely be, “Can we afford not to?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be very hard for people to admit the truth, to acknowledge the truth, even to learn the truth, when it is a truth which they find so difficult to accept. So truth is not easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the great American poet Maya Angelou said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“History, despite its wrenching pain, cannot be un-lived, but if faced with courage, need not be lived again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to face our truth with courage if we are to build a sustainable peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reconciliation, I think is a process which looks outward and forward and which brings together elements which belong together, but which have been torn apart. In our Church sense we talk about reconciliation as being the process of acknowledgement of wrong doing, of repentance, of a commitment to make reparation and a desire never to be separated again, and of forgiveness. That process can apply to society. It needs trust and trust has been absent from our society, and from so many others which have been in conflict for decades. Reconciliation is about not letting the past dictate the future. It is about bringing together the goodness of all the disparate parts of our divided community and working on those foundations, rather than allowing the evil of the past to separate us in the future, as it has divided us in the past.  That, I think has been much of the focus of the workmen Corrymeela over the decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;healing&quot;&gt;Healing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also inherent in this agenda of truth and reconciliation, the concept of healing. I think healing is a process which is personal and inward looking. It is of the soul and the mind and the body. Healing is the balm for the soul, the mending of the broken, the fusing of the shattered, the making whole of that which was torn apart. I do not believe that societies heal. I believe that they may be reconciled, but it is the wounds and pains of individuals which can be healed. And sometimes it is through truth that people are finally healed.  It is fundamental to what we believe as Christians. As Jesus said “”If you continue in My word, then you are truly disciples of Mine; and you will know the truth, and the truth will make you free.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these things must come together to create a functional society. If we do not allow truth, if we resist reconciliation, the trauma and anguish, the unfinished business will continue to echo through our days, until eventually we are forced to deal with them. And the suspicions and distrust which run through our society, reaching to the very highest levels will continue to undermine our fragile peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are the foundations, the values, upon which we can build the structures identified in the Storming House Agreement, to allow us to consolidate our peace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I saw a brave mother, all of 5 feet tall, take the arm of her six foot tall teenage son and drag him away from the protest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Courage&lt;/strong&gt; is necessary – I think of one situation in Harryville, during the protests. I saw a brave mother, all of 5 feet tall, take the arm of her six foot tall teenage son and drag him away from the protest. She must have destroyed his street cred. but she was a brave woman.  I have watched leading republicans protect British soldiers from attack during rioting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our politicians need the courage  to work across our divisions, so that people are not trapped in local government regimes which are manifestly sectarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need the courage to name the wrongdoing (such as the lack of provision, the inappropriate locations in which people were dumped in social housing without access to shops and schools) , not to deny it but to build beyond it; to face what has gone wrong in the past, and to care for people who present as the problem as well as those who think they have the solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need genuine &lt;strong&gt;compassion and love&lt;/strong&gt;, walking with people in their suffering  and their healing.  We need to really listen to those who live in the difficult areas and facilitating and enabling their involvement in the identification and implementation of solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need all the key agencies and organisations to be flexible, to acknowledge past failings, and to work together constructively to build the future, particularly those responsible for housing, transport, community regeneration, city and county authorities and the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is work in which wounds can be opened, and people know again the pain of their anguish&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have come now to a place and a time when we can very often carefully and respectfully meet and talk about these things, to enable the understanding which will allow us to embed peace in our society. We can work together to improve our environment. We can try and create the situation in which instead of building more peace walls, as we are at the moment we can start dismantling them – but only when those who live within the shadow of their protection want them to be dismantled. Because we want our people to feel as safe as they can. We want them to have jobs and training and hope.  It is work in which wounds can be opened, and people know again the pain of their anguish, but sometimes the opening of the wound brings with it healing and healing enables the person to move forward, and so, slowly, slowly we move to peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt; is the product of that moving towards peace. Healing, acknowledgment of truth, reconciliation will all bring us to trust the there and ourselves. We need to develop our capacity to trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need &lt;strong&gt;integrity&lt;/strong&gt; - integrity in each of us, so that we determine how we will act in accordance with what we believe, with the values which underpin our lives, and we need absolute integrity in our governance and in those who govern us. And to ensure integrity we need effective modes of accountability, so that we can weed out any corruption or partiality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So those are my four pillars upon which we can build a sustainable and genuine peace: courage, compassion and love, trust, and integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they form the basis for action, then we can build the structures of the Stormont House Agreement in a way which will not divide us. In caring for and in respecting the dignity of who still bear the wounds and trauma of the Troubles we may bring some peace into individual lives, and prevent that ongoing trans-generational trauma to which I referred earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key then to our ability to build a sustainable peace is individual action.  Necessary change must occur in each heart and mind. It is the work which Corrymeela was founded for, and it is not yet done.  So much more is required of each of us so that we can reach out in generosity to all our brothers and sisters. The way we do it will depend on our situations: but if those in government act with courage, compassion and love, integrity and trust they will do what is right for us, our limited resources will be spent for the common good, rather than in perpetuating division by building multiple sports stadiums and policing protest. If those in communities, whether the community of the family, the community of the school or the workplace, the community of council or the Assembly, or the wider community really seek to build peace in every interaction of every day, there will be peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it is perhaps appropriate to end with some words which are attributed to St Augustine of Hippo, and to bring to God in thanksgiving and hope this, your work of peace making.
God of our life, there are days when the burdens we carry chafe our shoulders and weigh us down; when the road seems dreary and endless, the skies grey and threatening; when our lives have no music in them,  and our hearts are lonely, and our souls have  lost their courage.  Flood the path with light, run our eyes to where the skies are full of promise; tune our hearts to brave music; give us the sense of comradeship with heroes and saints of every age; and so quicken our spirits that we may be able to encourage the souls of all who journey with us on the road of life, to Your honour and glory. 
Nuala O’Loan&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//conflict-resolution/building-the-peace-getting-the-foundations-right/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//conflict-resolution/building-the-peace-getting-the-foundations-right/</guid>
        
        
        <category>conflict-resolution</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2nd Policing Global Cities Conference</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The topic which we will discuss is one of the utmost importance to all countries – waging the war against terrorism, whilst ensuring that normal policing operates in so far as is possible for the benefit of all the people, both those from communities in which terrorists function, and those which may be almost untouched by bombs, shootings and all the connected criminality which accompanies terrorist activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When criminal and terrorist activity are simultaneously been part of the ordinary business of policing, many challenges follow from this, for the police and other security forces, for communities and for individuals. Policing must be delivered in a constantly changing situation. There will be police officers who police for the thirty years of their normal police career, without ever drawing their gun, apart from during training. There will be others whose careers are spent in places which are very dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must first explain to you that in Northern Ireland the term paramilitary does not refer to an agency of the state as it does for example in the United States – it refers to those involved in unlawful armed activities for a political purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nominally in Northern Ireland we are at peace, but there is another story to be told. In the year ending 31 March, 2015, PSNI statistics demonstrate that there were 3 deaths due to the security situation, 94 shootings and assaults by paramilitaries of which 48 were by loyalists and 46 by republicans. There were 73 shooting incidents and 26 bombing incidents. 58 firearms were recovered, 22.94 kgs of explosives and 4,569 rounds of explosives were recovered. 227 people were arrested under the Terrorism Act and 35 people were charged. During 2013-2014 government statistics show that 18 people were convicted under the Terrorism legislation and 88 charges were made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In England and Wales 230 people were arrested for terrorist offences (only 45 of them under the Terrorism Acts) compared to Northern Ireland’s 227. There is a much higher charging rate in England and Wales: 52% or 119 people were charged. 27 people were convicted of terrorism related offences compared with 18 in Northern Ireland. There are 58m people in England and Wales compared with 1.8m in Northern Ireland. We still have a significant problem with going terrorism!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Community policing and counter-terrorist policing
Our experience of policing terrorism has taught us that the way in which policing is conducted in these circumstances is enormously important. As I said, ordinary policing has to continue side by side with counter-terrorist policing. In conducting counter terrorist policing the contribution that the people can make should never be ignored. Terrorists need community support. They need places to store things, eyes to watch what is going on, safe houses, and many other things (and people very often do these things for them because they know that if they do not help they will be attacked and even murdered.) There will be those within the community who can alert the security forces to what is going on. It may be dangerous for them to do so. However they may wish to help. Where communities, for whatever reason, harbour terrorists, those communities will become dangerous places for the police and security forces. We had 302 police officers, and 709 military personnel murdered, as well as some 2600 civilians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However there is a big risk that in trying to deal with this situation those who live in these areas will become alienated form the forces of law and order. Working with those members of the community who are committed to the rule of law should be a priority where possible so that the them and us situation does not evolve. International experience indicates that if policing is repressive and does not comply with legal and basic human rights standards, then the people become alienated from policing, and in turn policing becomes less effective. One of the biggest dangers of counter-terrorist policing, and of the policing of international serious organised crime must be that it will grow the very problem which it seeks to defeat. Lawful and Human Rights compliant policing will encourage the mass of the community to co-operate with the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Northern Ireland there was significant alienation of the people from the police on both sides of our divided community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—The Northern Ireland policing solution
Our policing situation was very difficult and as part of the negotiations for peace, following the IRA ceasefire in 1994 an Independent Commission of Inquiry into policing was established. The Commission was tasked to consult widely and make recommendations, based on a set of core principles. These were that the new Police Service should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be professional, effective and efficient;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be fair and impartial;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be free from partisan political control;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be accountable, both under the law for its actions and to the community it serves;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be representative of the society it polices;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operate within a coherent and cooperative criminal justice system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those I think are basic principles which should underpin the operation of policing globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important too to observe that in a conflicted society, policing is but one element of the process which deals with security and crime. It will be profoundly important that there is demonstrable adherence to the Rule of Law in all its manifestations There must be a functioning constitutional government, including a criminal justice system with skilled and professional prosecution and defence lawyers. There must be an adequate and effective intelligence process, and there must be accountability by the police for the extensive powers which they hold over people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Police officers have powers to arrest, detain, enter homes and offices and search them, and to take away material which may be relevant to a criminal investigation. They prepare the prosecution files which inform a court in its deliberations as to the innocence or guilt of a defendant. They also have limited power to use force which is proportionate and necessary when carrying out their duties. It is those powers, and the occasions of abuse of them which necessitate accountability for the systems, policies, practices and manner of policing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Why do things go wrong?
When contemplating how to achieve the best possible policing in a terrorist situation there are a number of factors which must be taken into account, because they are the factors which will either prevent or contribute to policing which is not consistent with the law or with the international standards. The question I want to address first is why do things go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The style of leadership and the institutional culture of the police service are the most important factors.  Excessive police use of force is very common in many countries, and is not seen as wrong, and treated as such, even when the force used is unnecessary and even unlawful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole communities, such as the Muslim community or the Catholic community in Northern Ireland must not be treated as the enemy. Police culture which adopts such thinking will always antagonise the law abiding members of the community and they will lose trust in policing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leadership is critical to preventing policing abuses – zero tolerance approaches to violations together with apologies by senior police commanders, and positive statements to police officers about the duty to uphold and protect the law, to respect communities, such as the Muslim community, have a significant impact on serving officers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where officers believe that there is a culture of impunity, they may combine that with an institutional culture which approves the use of force, resulting in violations by police officers of the law. Where they know that there will be a reckoning this will impact down the line – even a few prosecutions and convictions can have a marked halo effect on the behaviour of colleagues.
Low pay and lack of equipment may be causative factors for poor policing. Where there is low pay a culture of corruption is much more common. In a counter terrorist situation this is profoundly important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of training and equipment will be a very important factor. Policing riots and demonstrations is a challenge. There are ways of doing riot control which will exacerbate an already bad situation. These must be avoided. Police officers must be properly equipped and trained so that they can withstand petrol bomb attacks etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of a clear code of ethics stating clearly what is expected of each police officer in the execution of their duty may also result in police wrongdoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policing must be fully accountable to independent investigation. In terror situations this is particularly important as it has the capacity to demonstrate the criminal or wrongful policing will be dealt with, and for police officers it means that those on the ground will know that when they have not done wrong but have been poorly led then their commanders will be accountable for their criminality or negligence too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As terrorism takes hold in any city or society, a number of consequences for policing which are common to conflict situations may emerge. In N. Ireland they included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The loss of police officers who were declared “a legitimate target” by the IRA. 303 0fficers have died;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anybody who worked for or with the police was also declared a legitimate target, that included civilians who worked on police boards, and police accountability organisations ;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure in terms of premises and equipment was lost;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeated bomb explosions which destroyed police stations also destroyed many of the investigation files, together with the various evidential exhibits. These were critical in the battle to bring the conflict to an end;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Terrorist attacks on forensic science laboratories led not only to extensive loss of evidence, but also to the loss of the facility and function, which also had a significant impact after the attacks as the labs had rebuild their capacity;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On 09 August 1971 hundreds of Republican men aged from 17 years old were interned neither awaiting trial nor convicted, for up to three years The sheer injustice of internment, and its economic and social consequences, in terms of the disruption of the economic life of those interned and the response to internment, caused massive resentment, generated huge resistance to the law and, it is widely thought in Northern Ireland that internment without trial was a significant recruiting agent for the IRA;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The use of unlawful interrogation techniques both during internment and investigation became such a cause for concern that the Irish Government brought proceedings against the British Government in the European Court of Human Rights which resulted in a finding that the UK had used techniques which amounted to inhuman and degrading treatment in breach of Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights. The interrogation techniques which had been used were wall-standing; hooding; subjection to noise; deprivation of sleep; deprivation of food and drink. The British Government gave a commitment that they would never be used again. There is evidence that they were used in Iraq;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The use of certain policing equipment such as rubber bullets, can cause problems, though I know many police forces across the world use on the basis that they are less than lethal. However they can be lethal. Their use led to further disconnection between the police and the people, particularly when children died from plastic bullet injuries;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A breakdown of normal policing activity which became secondary to the policing of the conflict. In some areas police could not answer a call for help for many hours, if at all. This enhanced the situation in which the community turned to the paramilitary/terrorist groups for help in matters which would normally involve the police. The paramilitaries, in their turn, recognised the opportunities arising for them in this situation;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As in many conflicts, the police were recognised and identified by many as a tool of one side (the Protestant state). 
Catholics joining the police service were targeted for assassination by the IRA. If they joined they very often could not return to their homes in republican areas. The number of Catholic police officers dropped to 7%. The police became even less representative of the community they served;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Police strategy and management became seriously weakened, leading to the lacunae which facilitated the operation of corruption, or as some call it, noble cause corruption, by some officers;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The anti-terrrorist arm of the police – the Special Branch, became very much separated from the rest of the force. Normal flows of intelligence to crime investigators became hampered, leading to frustration among CID officers. It was described to the Patten Commission by police officers as “a force within a force”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the absence of laws or effective internal controls regulating the handling, control and management of informants serious problems developed, leading to a situation in which some informants were able to commit serious crimes without being made amenable for those crimes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unlawful techniques included:
- Failure to arrest informants for crimes to which those informants had allegedly confessed, or to treat such informants as suspects for crime;  
- Creating interview notes which were deliberately misleading; by failing to record and maintain original interview notes and by failing to record notes of meetings with informants;  
- The failure to deal properly with information received from informants, so that informants were able to avoid investigation and detection for crime;  
- Arresting informants suspected of murder then subjecting them to lengthy sham interviews by their own handlers at which they were not challenged and then releasing them on the authorisation of the handler;  
- Not recording in investigation papers the fact that an informant was suspected of a crime despite the fact that he had been arrested and interviewed for that crime;  
- Failing to take steps to hinder an attempted bombing by the establishment of an operation either to disrupt or arrest the alleged perpetrators whose names were known to Special Branch;  
- Giving instructions to junior officers that records should not be completed, and that there should be no record of the incident concerned;
- Ensuring the absence of any official record linking a Special Branch informant to the possession of explosives which may, and were thought, according to private police records, to have been used in a particular crime;  
- Withholding information from CID that the UVF had sanctioned an attack;  
concealing from CID intelligence that named persons, including an informant or informants, had been involved in particular crimes;  
withholding information about the location to which a group of murder suspects had allegedly fled after a murder;  
- The concealment on a number of occasions of intelligence indicating that up to three informants had been engaged together in murders and a particular crime or crimes;  
- Routinely destroying all Tasking and Co-ordinating Group original documentary records so as to conceal an informant’s involvement in crime; 
- Destroying or losing forensic exhibits such as metal bars and tape lifts;  
- A few police officers become involved in murder and others became involved in the in corruption that is collusion, through failing to act professionally, and in some cases through the protection of those involved in murder bombing and shooting;
- Carrying on policing during this protracted and terrible period inevitably led to serious levels of post traumatic stress disorder both among serving and retired police officers;
- There were allegations during the Troubles that police operated a shoot to kill policy – using lethal force where lesser force would have sufficed to bring terrorists under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—The impact on the people and police of Northern Ireland
Police officers became focussed on the need to stay alive. Their performance of their policing duties in very difficult areas inevitably took second place to their wish to stay alive. For their families there was the daily fear that the mother or father, husband, wife, daughter or son who went out to work as a police officer would be murdered that day and would not come home to them. Police officers in this situation often kept their occupation secret, so as to protect not only themselves but their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Northern Ireland there was a very odd situation in which officers of the rank of constable and sergeant wore green shirts, while other officers wore white shirts. The green shirts were procured by the Police Authority at great expense as they had to be specially dyed to get the right shade of green. Since police officers were the only people wearing shirts of this particular shade of green, their wives could not hang them out to dry when they washed them as this would identify the officer as a member of the RUC. A burden for those who washed the shirts, but I could never understand why all the officers did not wear white shirts as they do now. It was one very simple solution to a nasty problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, what happened in Northern Ireland as in so many conflict situations was that community confidence in policing diminished, and by the end of the Troubles this had happened in both loyalist and republican communities. As the police were criticised and as the calls for reform became more strident, police morale began to suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this the reality is that those engaged in armed conflict need the protection and support of the community from which they operate. They need places to store things, eyes to watch what is going on, safe houses, and many other things (and people very often do these things for them because they know that if they do not help they will be attacked and even murdered.). Where communities, for whatever reason, harbour terrorists, those communities will become dangerous places for the police.. There will be those within the community who can alert the security forces to what is going on. It may be dangerous for them to do so. In Northern Ireland we saw many people abducted, tortured and left dead, usually in lonely country roads as a warning to others not to engage with the security forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Community policing and counter-terrorist policing
Our experience of policing terrorism has taught us that the way in which policing is conducted in these circumstances is enormously important. Despite all the difficulties, ordinary policing has to continue side by side with counter-terrorist policing. Ultimately policing can only be effective with the consent of those who are policed. In conducting counter terrorist policing the contribution that the people can make should never be ignored. International experience indicates that if policing is repressive and does not comply with legal and basic human rights standards, then the people become alienated from policing, and in turn policing becomes less effective. One of the biggest dangers of counter-terrorist policing, and of the policing of international serious organised crime must be that it will grow the very problem which it seeks to defeat. Lawful and Human Rights compliant policing will encourage the mass of the community to co-operate with the police.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//policing/policing-global-cities-conference/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//policing/policing-global-cities-conference/</guid>
        
        
        <category>policing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Living the Christian Call - Prophecy and Witness</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon. It is very encouraging to see you all coming together as a Presentation family and to be part of this experience and to witness the richness with which your faith graces the work that you do. I have known of the Presentation sisters for many years and of the wonderful work which you do here in Ireland and across the world, and of course your foundress, Honora “Nano” Nagle, who worked incessantly and against all the odds, was declared venerable on 31 October 2013 by Pope Francis. I am sure that that was moment of great rejoicing for you, and an extraordinary affirmation not only of Nano Nagle, but also of her legacy and all of you and the work which you do are part of her legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You asked me to talk today about ‘Living the Christian call: prophecy and witness’. I found this slightly challenging. So I went away and read about prophecy and witness. It was confusing. Then I found this statement about a man I admire very much. His name is Jean Vanier and I met him one day in Derry when he came to speak to about a thousand 16/17 year olds in the Millennium Forum. His theme was very simple “Jesus loves you.” Have you seen him? He is very tall and very thin, and a bit dishevelled!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then he began to talk and he talked for about 50 minutes on the theme ‘Jesus loves you’, and you could have heard a pin drop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He ambled on to an empty stage and sat on the only piece of furniture on it - a tall bar stool. Then he explained that he was so old that he needed to sit down. Then he began to talk and he talked for about 50 minutes on the theme ‘Jesus loves you’, and you could have heard a pin drop. None of the normal shuffling and whispering and texting etc! Just absolute silence. It was extraordinary. Until, having told his life story and explained who he was and what his life had been, he asked the question, “who could love me?” and a little voice piped up “I love you”. It was little girl of 15 or so who has Downs Syndrome. She articulated what everyone thought. For he had described a life of many challenges and ultimately great heroism and incredible gentleness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure that you all know his story. For Jean Vanier was the man who established the L’Arche community which now provides homes for people with learning and physical disabilities where they live with able bodied people who live with them and facilitate their lives, whatever it takes. And some of them are so profoundly disabled that it takes an awful lot. But those who work with them learn what Jean Vanier learned early on in his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr James D Conley, speaking in Nebraska 2013 said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Through our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ, God has given us the ability to see all people through his eyes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I would submit to you that this new way of seeing is the beginning of the Christian vocation to prophecy. A prophet sees the world as God does — sees the world in truth — and then proclaims Christ’s Kingdom. For fifty years, Jean Vanier has seen the world in truth; and in the witness of L’Arche communities, has demonstrated the goodness of the Lord’s enduring love in a profoundly prophetic way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So maybe it is much more helpful to ditch all the definitions and say that we just have to look at people like Jean Vanier to see Christ’s call to holiness, which is what prophecy and witness are about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope Francis in his text on the opening of the Holy Year of Consecrated Life, last November, said this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I invite every Christian community to experience this Year above all as a moment of thanksgiving to the Lord and grateful remembrance for all the gifts we continue to receive, thanks to the sanctity of founders and foundresses, and from the fidelity to their charism shown by so many consecrated men and women. I ask all of you to draw close to these men and women, to rejoice with them, to share their difficulties and to assist them, to whatever degree possible, in their ministries and works, for the latter are, in the end, those of the entire Church. Let them know the affection and the warmth which the entire Christian people feels for them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think that that is what we are doing today. We are celebrating with the Presentation Sisters their achievements and their charism which could well be described as prophecy and witness, for the way in which they have chosen to lead their lives has been inspired by Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just think about it. In 1754 a woman of 36 began a school for 30 poor children, secretly, in defiance of the Penal Laws. Within a year she had 200 students. Within 15 years, 7 schools here in Cork. They were a way fighting the root causes of poverty and the systemic injustice of the Penal Laws. She knew that children needed to learn that they were loved and valued, and that they needed skills and talents to earn their living, and in all that she did, she told them about Jesus, about his blessed Mother Mary, about God and about the power of the Holy Spirit. And, if that were not enough she visited the sick, the elderly, the imprisoned and the destitute – often at night, walking through the dark and dangerous streets of Cork by the light of a flickering lantern. Then in 1783 she built a home for aged and destitute women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a male-dominated society in which what she was doing in establishing schools was against the law&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What an achievement in 18th century Ireland, an Ireland of immense poverty and deprivation, an Ireland in which there was little in the way of policing and protection for the poor and those who sought to help them, a male-dominated society in which what she was doing in establishing schools was against the law. But she knew it was morally right. Prophetically she led people to understand what needed to be done, she witnessed by doing it and she did it all in the name of the Lord Jesus. So that was prophecy and witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned over the years that life can be very challenging, and that we can underestimate our capacity for prophecy and witness. We can misunderstand the effects of what we do and say. I have learned too that this life of mine is, in many ways, not mine. I do not know when I will die. I only know that I will, and I have learned that this time here on earth is very precious and that it was given to us so that we could try to live in love for others and through them for Christ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I still have my L plates, and I am conscious that I am in the presence of those who know so much more and have given so much more than I can ever hope to do. Being a Christian is really very simple though, and as Pope Francis said two years ago on Pentecost Sunday:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We have to let ourselves be flooded by the Holy Spirit’s light, because He introduces us to the Truth of God, who is the only Lord of our life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You cannot be a ‘part time’ Christian, [a Christian] in some moments, under some circumstances, for certain decisions. You are a Christian in every moment! The truth of Christ, which the Holy Spirit teaches and gives us, involves, for always and entirely, our daily life.”
 
We believe that, some perhaps more than others, some of us at some times and some at others. We believe that we are on a journey in faith, that God did make us, that he has a plan for each of us, some special calling which he has not given to another, as Cardinal Newman told us, and that our lives here are to be lived not, in Francis’ words, as part-time Christians, but rather in love for the God who made us, and in love for each other and the magnificent world in which we live. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a theoretical vague love, rather living in love will inevitably take us to places to which we would rather not go, will present us with challenges we would rather not have, and will demand of us that we give without limit as Christ gave himself for us.  Fr Robert Barron said in his book ‘The Strangest Way’ said that our faith is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“a form of life, a path that one walks. It is a way of seeing, a frame of mind, an attitude, but more than this, it is a manner of moving and acting, standing and relating. It is not simply a matter of the mind but of the body as well. In fact, one could say that Christianity is not real until it has insinuated itself into the blood and the bones, until it becomes an instinct, as much physical as spiritual. Perhaps, the most direct description is this: Christianity, the way of Jesus Christ, is a culture, a style of life supported by a unique set of convictions, assumptions, hopes, and practices.””&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this description of faith, because in some ways it manages to encompass not only what can seem the illogicalities of our faith, which, in my good times, I know as simply the limitations of my understanding, but also the magnificence and the profound and inexplicable comfort that I know in the sheer fact that God is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your role in delivering Catholic Education in the modern world is a work of both prophecy and witness. You do it in a world in which many of those whom you teach are disconnected from faith as many of us understand it, in which families inhabit a different world you face many challenges and as the Pope said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Every educator – and the Church as a whole is an educating mother – is required to change, in the sense of knowing how to communicate with the young.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said they must be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“the living presence of the Gospel in the field of education, science and culture”__ and must __“know how to enter, with courage, into the Areopagus of contemporary cultures and to initiate dialogue, aware of the gift they are able to offer to all.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Francis addressed the challenges you face, saying, __“Catholic schools and universities are attended by many students who are not Christian or do not believe. Catholic educational institutions offer to all an approach to education that has as its aim the full development of the person, which responds to the right of every person to access to knowledge. However, they are also called upon to offer, with full respect for the freedom of each person and using the methods appropriate to the scholastic environment, the Christian belief, that is, to present Jesus Christ as the meaning of life, the cosmos and history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Jesus began to proclaim the good news of the ‘Galilee of the people’, a crossroads of people, diverse in terms of race, culture and religion. This context resembles today’s world, in certain respects. The profound changes that have led to the ever wider diffusion of multicultural societies require those who work in the school or university sector to be involved in educational itineraries involving comparison and dialogue, with a courageous and innovative fidelity that enables Catholic identity to encounter the various ‘souls’ of multicultural society.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do live in such a different world - you must educate children who live in a virtual world, who are subject to massive pressures, many of whose parents have moved on from traditional values, where children may have three parents, or two parents of the same sex, where siblings may not have a common father, where people may be unable work for generations, where they may have lost their homes to the recession, or live in fear of losing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also live in a world in which the Catholic people of Ireland can be very proud of their Catholic past. So much was given by so many in so many different places by Irish Catholics. And today the people of Ireland are among the most generous in the world. The World Giving Index was published a few months ago. It reports that in 2013, when Ireland was in such a difficult place its people still managed to be ranked 4th in the world in giving behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just behind Myanmar and the US which were joint first and Canada which was third. A very significant achievement for the people of Ireland. It measured helping a stranger, donating money and volunteering time. The UK came 7th! That is real witness, and whilst many people claim that we live in post Catholic Ireland I know that so much of the volunteering, the giving and the helping is still done because people believe and can see the value of witness, even when they don’t volunteer themselves, they may give to organisations like the SVP which does so much good for people across the world, and it is a Catholic organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Church has much to do in this world, and Catholic education must accept the many challenges its pupils face and help them, never forgetting what it is really all about. 
 
Pope Francis on the first day of his Papacy said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We can walk all we want, we can build many things, but if we don’t proclaim Jesus Christ, something is wrong. We would become a compassionate NGO and not a Church which is the bride of Christ.”  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this business of prophecy and witness, part of our call to holiness, requires of us the effort to grow our relationship with Jesus and through him with God. So our schools - they must be more than just professional educational institutions.  They have to be places in which Jesus Christ is both proclaimed and encountered through the daily interactions between staff and pupils.  That is quite a challenging thought, isn’t it? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Evangelii Gaudium Pope Francis talked at length about the problems of the impact of the secular world which relive.  He identifies education as a solution to secularization:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The process of secularization tends to re­duce the faith and the Church to the sphere of the private and personal. Furthermore, by com­pletely rejecting the transcendent, it has produced a growing deterioration of ethics, a weakening of the sense of personal and collective sin, and a steady increase in relativism. These have led to a general sense of disorientation, especially in the periods of adolescence and young adulthood which are so vulnerable to change…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We are living in an information-driven society which bombards us indiscriminately with data — all treated as being of equal importance — and which leads to remarkable superficiality in the area of moral discernment. In response, we need to provide an education which teaches crit­ical thinking and encourages the development of mature moral values.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He praises Catholic schools and colleges for their contributions around the world, yet acknowledges that those contributions are often not appreciated when they are counter-cultural, as is often necessary to remain faithful to Catholic teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wonders that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Again and again, the Church has acted as a mediator in find­ing solutions to problems affecting peace, social harmony, the land, the defence of life, human and civil rights, and so forth. And how much good has been done by Catholic schools and uni­versities around the world! This is a good thing. Yet, we find it difficult to make people see that when we raise other questions less palatable to public opinion, we are doing so out of fidelity to precisely the same convictions about human dignity and the common good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You really do have such an important job to do. But I think we always have to remember what really makes Catholic education different from other forms of education, and wonder is it really different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we do not know it but it is true that the most important thing for each of us is our relationship with Jesus and through him with God. His presence in our lives is a blessing which enables, enlightens, comforts, consoles and encourages, which makes all right things possible, and which gives purpose to all that we are, all that we have, and all that we do. This is true of the children you educate too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you face the demands of curriculum, of paperwork and inevitable beaurocracy, of planning, marking, and all the other things you have to do, it can seem almost that remembering that the children need to see the face of Christ in you each day is just too much to ask.   But they spend so many hours of their young lives in your company, exposed to your ways of doing things, learning from your behaviour.  That may well be the greatest challenge of working in a Catholic school!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;St Paul wrote that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When I was a child I spoke like a child, thought like a child, understood like a child, but when I became a man I put away childish things”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That should be true of all of us.  Those of my generation who grew up as Catholics were taught our faith in a very structured, way using very particular language - rosaries, benediction, lighting candles, placing all our trust in the Lord.. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those days can seem perhaps rosier than they were.  Everything had a structure, a place, a time, a process, but of course it did not always mean that we were able to understand or even to accept what we had learned.  The process of growing in faith to which we have been committed over the past year can be a very difficult one, not least because life throws at us that which we do not expect, that which does not fit neatly within the confines of that very disciplined, structured religion.  The answers given to me in my early days  to the problems of death and poverty and social injustice were very limited - they had the essence of truth, but they did not answer my questions.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one of the problems, or perhaps one of the blessings, is that we go on needing answers to inexplicable problems.  So do the children whom you teach. Do you, like me, find yourself often asking questions and trying to find answers, trying to rationalise what you believe and to understand better? The psalmist knew this thousands of years ago when he wrote,&lt;strong&gt;“Your face, Lord, I will seek. Do not hide your face from me,”&lt;/strong&gt; And so we search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as we do so it has seemed to me that we are faced with even more questions.  They are not easy questions. A child dies of hunger every 5 seconds in our world. 12 a minute. 540 in the 45 minutes during which I will speak to you. Starvation is a very hard way to die. Why can’t we get it right as a world?
 
Finding some sort of answer or some way of living with those inexplicable tragedies takes time, and I think it takes a process of maturity in each of us. It takes a process of listening and thinking and talking about it and praying about it, and even fighting with God. Not a pleasant thought but maybe if we are honest we will acknowledge that just once or twice we may have engaged the Almighty in a spirit of anger and despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I think for children and young people life is in some ways more heightened than for those who have more years, and so the responses and the decisions can be more immediate and less tempered.  So in the middle of all that teaching and educating and forming young minds, you and they may be caught in the middle of some drama or tragedy, either within your own life or those of the children whom you teach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;it was as if we were held by their prayer
 
One of my experiences has been that at times I have felt literally incapable of dealing with what has happened  - things like death, or the savage attack which left our third son lying unconscious on a road in Belfast, broken and terribly injured.  It was just too horrendous, too terrible. and at that time so many people got in touch with us telephoning, writing, calling, coming to the hospital, stopping us in the street and it was as if we were held by their prayer, and as if our son, who was so hurt, was cradled by those prayers, just as he was surrounded by the Mass Cards which I put all around his bedroom, so that when he wakened from his sleep through the weeks and months of his recovery he would see them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet Christ in so many people who come into our lives, sometimes for a very short period, even for minutes, sometimes for years, and walk the journey with us, relations, friends, teachers, medical professionals.  There are so many ways and so many occasions on which we meet the Lord, through the loving witness of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope Benedict said in his final address that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Lord has given us many days of sunshine and light breezes, days when the fishing was plentiful, but also times when the water was rough and the winds against us, just as throughout the whole history of the Church, when the Lord seemed to be sleeping. But I always knew that the Lord is in that boat and I always knew that the boat of the Church is not mine, not ours, but is His. And the Lord will not let it sink. He is the one who steers her, of course also through those He has chosen because that is how He wanted it. This was and is a certainty that nothing can tarnish. And that is why my heart today is filled with gratitude to God, because He never left—the whole Church or me—without His consolation, His light, or His love.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for me somehow, even when things have seemed pretty grim, I have always known that at the heart of my life, at the core of my being, is the love that God has for me, inexplicable as that seems to me when I contemplate myself. Jean Vanier asked that question too. Who could love me? Maybe we all ask it at some time in our lives. Yet we are loved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, you are called to a very special vocation, teaching. It has to be a vocation. I cannot comprehend how one individual can spend all their days looking after 30 or so children, especially as you do, during their teenage years, when the  battle to work out who they are and why they are here is probably at its strongest, when they may  feel compelled to test everything and everyone!  I can think of nothing harder. I could not do it. You do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the doing of it you may be the person who makes a child’s life possible that day, who shows a child that they are lovable, despite the fact that everything seems to tell them they are not, who leads them to understand that they can do things which they just don’t believe they can do, who listens when they need to talk about things that they can to to nobody else about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;your hands are the hands by which he blesses these his little ones&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may indeed be the face of Christ of them. Perhaps when you feel tired and possibly a bit dispirited or demotivated later in the year, you may remember this fact, that for some little child you may be the face, the hands, the eyes, the ears of Christ, and that your hands are the hands by which he blesses these his little ones, for he has no hands here on earth, as St Theresa of Avila told us. I have seen much blessedness in Catholic schools, much care and compassion leading the children forward into a future in which there is hope.
 
One of the things our young people need to know is that they are called, and that how they do things, and the reasons why they do them, in this complex modern world are very important. We live in a world of instant communication - a world in which in seconds a message can travel across the world on Facebook and Twitter… that is a very powerful situation. We can use it. We have much greater access to visuals - to pictures, scenes, they can all inform our thinking and the ay in which we develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about Pope Francis and some of the things he has done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shower blocks for the homeless, inviting them for dinner, taking them into the Sistine chapel and talking to each one of them, burying the one who died in the Square in the basilica, honoured in life as he had not been honoured in death. These things make people think. they make them uncomfortable too on occasion. They challenge us all to move out of our comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has done it too in reversing the merciless decision to exclude people for so many reasons telling priests to baptise children when the mother asks for baptism even if her circumstances do not meet church requirements, demonstrating humility on so many occasions. things of which we as a church can be proud, and things which we must, in our turn, emulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a way parents can hope that you will be able to do something they cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes parents want their children to learn about and grow in faith, even though they no longer engage with religious practice.  It is not easy to explain all this.  In a way parents can hope that you will be able to do something they cannot.  Maybe like St Augustine, and like me, they are saying , &lt;strong&gt;“Lord make me holy but not just yet.”&lt;/strong&gt;  Yet still they want their children to have the benefits of being in the presence of those who commit their lives to Christ, possibly falteringly, but in faith. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope Benedict XVI speaking to young people in Scotland in 2010 said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What God wants for each of you is that you should become holy.  He loves you more than you could ever begin to imagine, and he wants the very best for you.  And by far the best thing is to grow in holiness…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few people who have not in the course of their lives met truly good people, holy people whose lives are lived in and for Christ, informed by the presence of the Holy Spirit and who know that they are on the way home to the Father who made them. They will probably not talk of these things. People generally don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However it is their constant references to the things of God, to thanking God for good things, for happy moments, for those whom he sends into our lives, for the world in which we  spend our lives, their prayer when things are difficult or when we face moments of grief and tragedy, their ability to live through the most difficult and challenging moments in faith, knowing that even when God seems not be there, he really is there, and it is just that we can not, for that moment, that time, hear his voice, which mark them as people of God. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They live their lives in witness and prophecy. For me, those people who have walked into my life, and there have been many of them, have enriched my life, helped me to come to some understanding of what may on occasion be apparently  inexplicable, and have given me the sense and the knowledge of the presence of God’s love in my life and of the impact of his grace on me.  It was not just their  kindness, their humanity, their goodness.  It was their faith which is so much more profound than that goodness,which helps me to comprehend the presence of God and which has helped me in the journey to try to know God, to love him and to serve him in all that I do and with all whom I meet, which is the essence of my existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may all sound a little garbled but I think it is the essence of faith and it gives a whole different meaning to life. It calls for a life of prophecy and witness. If a child is to grow in faith then they need as much exposure as possible and as many opportunities as possible to be with people who share that belief.  Those opportunities will be greater in a school dedicated to God, in which children learn every day about the fact that God loves them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope Francis once said that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“school is the first society to integrate with the family. The school and the family are not in opposition to one another. They are complementary, and therefore it is important that they collaborate between themselves with mutual respect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He recalled the African proverb: &lt;strong&gt;“It takes a village to raise a child.”&lt;/strong&gt; He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Developing a sense of truth, of what is good and beautiful, is the mission of schools.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If something is true, it is good and beautiful; if it is beautiful, it is good and true; if it is good, it is true and it is beautiful. And together, these elements enable us to grow and help us to love life, even when we are not well, even in the midst of many problems. True education enables us to love life and opens us to the fullness of life,”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that this is not always the case. Children and parents, and of course many teachers are also parents, are acutely sensitive to the behaviour of those in authority or with responsibility in their school. They will see &lt;strong&gt;‘Do as I say, not as I do’&lt;/strong&gt; as an example of hypocrisy at best, and of lack of lived faith at worst. They will see it where a child in difficulties is excluded or expelled because they are too much trouble, and no-one is prepared to work out how to make it possible for them to stay in school.  There can be no effective communication of faith where children are taught to love one another, but do not themselves experience love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course children are like older people.  Some of them are very easy to love, very engaged in school, and very cooperative.  Others, for a myriad of reasons, may be hostile, negative and uncooperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the essence of Catholic spirituality for each of them is their individual relationship with God&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in your schools you are uniquely placed to ensure that there is a connectedness between the spirituality which the school seeks to promote and the daily life of the school, between life in school and the greater world around the children. You can help children to understand that the essence of Catholic spirituality for each of them is their individual relationship with God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will learn that best by being in the company of those who themselves believe in God and believe that he loves them and holds them in the palm of his hand, like the little old man who sat in a French church for long hours each day, and who, when asked why he did so, is said to have replied ‘I am watching God watching me’. If children are in places where they meet those who truly believe they will come to know that tenderness. I know that it can be very difficult, but you are the blessing which God has sent them today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can show the children too that they may be a blessing to others. You offer children throughout their schooldays the opportunity to engage in the work of justice, to be fundraiser for the poor, to help those less privileged than they are, to know that there are children in the world who are always hungry but that they can do something to help, to see all the children of the world as their brothers and sisters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they grow older they may become aware of opportunities, through school and church to go and work with others in need, building houses, working in orphanages, doing all in the name of the Lord, experiences through which they may become better people and through which they will understand that they too can make a difference in the world. And in so doing they witness to what they believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the work which you do,  it is great work. You have great opportunities, though I know that they will not always seem like opportunities! My guess is that each of you will at some stage have met a teacher who inspired you. I remember when I was 17, doing my A levels. My father had died four years previously, my mother had struggled with ill health and grief over those years, two of my brothers were very ill and life just seemed impossible. I was a boarder at school, and there came a day when I just felt A levels and life at school was irrelevant and that there was no hope for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As I stood on the platform waiting for the train, she appeared with a packed lunch for me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I went to a good nun who had kept me going over the four years, and told her I was leaving.  I would not do my A levels.  I had had enough.  And she tried to dissuade me, pointing out that hope lay through A levels and education into the future. But I left anyway, catching the bus down to the railway station, and as I stood on the platform waiting for the train, she appeared with a packed lunch for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went home that day, wondering in a slightly bemused way at the packed lunch.  When I got home I realised that this was not going to solve anything, and so after a few hours I went back to school and the rest is history.  It was her kindness, but above all that simple act that said if you must do this thing that I don’t want you to do, then go with my blessing and some food for the journey, that gave me a different understanding of where I was in the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My guess is that you too will make such a difference for a child whom you encounter in the course of your working day.  And you know something, you may never even know what it is that you have done.  But you will have made such a difference because you care and because you want to do more than teach a subject. You want to educate a child and to help to prepare them to take their place in the world, filled with hope, and with the gift of prophecy and the courage to witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope Francis said that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Prophets receive from God the ability to scrutinize the times in which they live and to interpret events: they are like sentinels who keep watch in the night and sense the coming of the dawn (cf. Is 21:11-12). Prophets know God and they know the men and women who are their brothers and sisters. They are able to discern and denounce the evil of sin and injustice. Because they are free, they are beholden to no one but God, and they have no interest other than God. Prophets tend to be on the side of the poor and the powerless, for they know that God himself is on their side.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is right but it is not easy in this world to challenge, to discern and to denounce sin and injustice. The reality is that those whom you might challenge are likely to be much more comfortable in their current state than in the place in which you want them to be. They may fight, they may try to marginalise you, they may comment dismissively on what you have said because you are Catholic or Christian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They may try to use the forces of the law against you - when I think back to some of the things I have seen in places where I have had the privilege to work for justice and peace - in Timor Leste, in Liberia, in South America, in Africa, I am only too aware that those who witness and who challenge may face the ultimate challenge and may end up paying the ultimate price - think of Archbishop Romero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 14 March 1977 he preached at the funeral Mass for his friend Fr. Rutilio Grande, SJ who was shot along with a young boy and an old man travelling from Aguilares to celebrate the Eucharist in El Paisnal. He must have known, having seen what he had seen, what danger he himself was in. Yet, speaking in the language of liberation theology, so important across South America, so challenging to the Church, yet so true in its post Vatican II demands that we really become a church for the poor, he said this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“My sisters and brothers, The liberation that Father Grande preached is inspired by faith, a faith that speaks to us about eternal life, a faith that he, with his face raised toward heaven and accompanied by two campesinos, offered up in its totality and perfection: liberation which culminates with happiness with God; liberation which brings about a repentance for sin, liberation based on Christ, the only saving power. This is the liberation that Father Rutilio Grande preached and therefore, he has lived the Church’s message.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later Archbishop Romero was murdered as he said Mass in his Cathedral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this business of giving witness and of being prophetic can be very challenging. And when that happens Pope Francis has some words for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In this period of crisis, today, it is important not to turn in on ourselves, burying our own talent, our spiritual, intellectual, and material riches, everything that the Lord has given us, but, rather to open ourselves, to be supportive, to be attentive to others. … Set your stakes on great ideals, the ideals that enlarge the heart, the ideals of service that make your talents fruitful.  Life is not given to us to be jealously guarded for ourselves, but is given to us so that we may give it in turn.”
– Audience, April 24&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you see, this business of witness and prophecy is to going to be easy, but I have learned that it can be, even in my very limited experience, so very fulfilling, for we are enriched as we give to others so much more than we can ever anticipate, and so much more than we are enriched by just living for ourselves to make a comfortable unchallenged life. I hope that through this coming together you will know one another better, and be better placed to help each other, to inspire each other and to be the face of Christ for each other and for the children. Then you will, as Pope Francis said, be happy for you will know God. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to close with some words words attributed to St. Augustine of Hippo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“God of our life, there are days when the burdens we carry chafe our shoulders and weigh us down; when the road seems dreary and endless, the skies grey and threatening; when our lives have no music in them,  and our hearts are lonely, and our souls have  lost their courage.  Flood the path with light, run our eyes to where the skies are full of promise; tune our hearts to brave music; give us the sense of comradeship with heroes and saints of every age; and so quicken our spirits that we may be able to encourage the souls of all who journey with us on the road of life, to Your honour and glory.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//faith/living-christian-call-prophecy-witness/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//faith/living-christian-call-prophecy-witness/</guid>
        
        
        <category>faith</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nuala O’Loan ‘appalled’ at Garda referendum involvement</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;respected-policing-expert-says-garda-are-engaging-in-political-campaign&quot;&gt;Respected policing expert says Gardaí are engaging in political campaign&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An internationally-respected expert on police accountability has said she was “appalled” to learn of Garda involvement in events pushing a ‘yes’ vote in the coming marriage referendum.
 
Baroness Nuala O’Loan, who between 2000 and 2007 was the first ombudsman for the Police Service of Northern Ireland, and who has advised on police accountability in countries as diverse as Canada, India, Brazil, and South Africa, told The Irish Catholic newspaper that “The police are supposed to be independent. Trust in them is dependent on that independence. This should not have happened.”
 
Responding to a recent piece in Garda Review by P.J. Stone, General Secretary of the Garda Representative Association, in which Mr Stone called on Gardaí to vote for marriage redefinition, Baroness O’Loan said: “Gardaí are not appointed to engage in political campaigns. That is what is going on here.”
 
“How can the public be expected to view them as impartial protectors of the law if they behave in this way,” she asked, adding, “They are representative of the State, and hence must remain apolitical during a referendum, I would argue.”
 
&amp;gt; They are representative of the State, and hence must remain apolitical during a referendum&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his article, Mr Stone attributed to bigotry opposition to a ‘yes’ vote, declared that without marriage redefinition Ireland was not ‘a real republic’, and assured Gardaí committed to campaigning for a ‘yes’ vote of the GRA leadership’s full support.
 
The article attempted to justify the GRA leadership’s unprecedented intervention by saying “this is the first time we have had the opportunity to recommend equality of our members as constitutional reform”.
 
Baroness O’Loan rejected this, saying, “Clearly the GRA are engaging in political action here, not representing their member’s interests in matters of welfare and efficiency,” pointing out that under the terms of the Garda Síochána Act 2005, the GRA’s role is carefully limited.
 
Lobbying for political purposes is not, she said, among the functions of the Garda Síochána.
 
It is true that under section 7 of the act, the Garda Síochána has a role in “vindicating the human rights of each individual”, but “there is no human right in law, international or European, to gay marriage”, according to the baroness, who in 2009 chaired a formal investigation into human rights in England and Wales for the UK Equality and Human Rights Commission.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//policing/garda-referendum-involvement/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//policing/garda-referendum-involvement/</guid>
        
        
        <category>policing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Women in the Church under Francis</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I chose to reflect on the position of women in the Church today in the context of what Michael Kelly describes as &lt;strong&gt;“the Francis effect”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that the population of the Catholic Church, as reported in 2014, is 1214m, we can safely assume that there are at least 600,000,000 Catholic women in the church today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we say about how women have reacted to the presence, the style and the words of Francis, more importantly, what is their position today? There is, of course, no one answer to this question. Little research has been done. Rather there may be a thousand answers. All I can do is to explore some of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I am fairly sure of is that there will be at least two sets of answers to these questions. One set relates more to women in religious life, the other to the rest of us. Those in religious life include a significant number of highly educated, very active women. There is a greater focus in the print media on them and their activities, than there is on the other group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women in religious life in the Church are a very significant group, diminishing down from 753,400 in 2006 to 713,000 in 2011 (the latest available figures published in the 2013 Pontifical Yearbook), yet still very influential in the areas in which they work and live. Some of them are actively seeking greater involvement in institutional Church life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of them are saddened that their life’s work is disregarded by the media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are vocal, energetic and very focussed. Others, especially in Ireland, are ageing, focussing much on their evangelisation, but equally on how they provide for and look after their ageing sisters. Many of them are saddened that their life’s work is disregarded by the media, which has a tendency to talk so much of the abuse scandals and less of the great contribution made by these noble women. I think that Pope Francis, in his simplify and directness, has brought them hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is it like to be a woman in the Catholic Church today? I asked a friend of mine what effect the election of Pope Francis had on her. She is an astute lady and her response was, as always, to the point. She said to me that he seemed so grounded and that he seemed to speak from the heart. She said that women were of the heart, that they lived at the heart of society in family, Church, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gave cause for hope that he did not seem to live alienated from the people. She talked of the experience of women over the years and how she hoped that women might now be treated differently, and might get an opportunity to contribute more than the things they had done so willingly in the past - the making of confirmation dinners, the cleaning of the Church etc. She said to me, &lt;strong&gt;“I think some of the things I might say would be helpful to priests!”&lt;/strong&gt; I know she was right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The women would then sit to eat afterwards as they do in many countries still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church in any part of the world, for all its dogma and teaching, is really reflective of the environment within which it operates. Historically women occupied a lesser role in most societies, even prior to the coming of Christ. We know that in his world, for example, the women would feed the men first (note the women would feed the men!) and then sit to eat afterwards as they do in many countries still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that it would not have been expected that he would call them his apostles - only men could be apostles But we know also of Phoebe and Priscilla, the Deaconesses. Phoebe, described by Paul as &lt;strong&gt;“a servant and a member of the church which is at Cenchrea”.&lt;/strong&gt; During the first few centuries of the church, the role of a woman servant (diakonos) was to care for fellow believers who were sick, for the poor, for strangers passing through, and for the imprisoned. They helped baptize and teach new women converts and instructed children and other women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, in society, women had a limited role which diminished over the centuries, until it reflected the Victorian experience of women - there to bear children, to serve, to nurture, to comfort and to obey. Then it began to grow again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That situation was reflected in the Church in which I grew up. It was a Church which was changing anyway. Women were no longer required to be churched - a process explained by some as being a blessing to mothers after childbirth, but experienced as being regarded by Church as a necessary cleansing after childbirth. Not an attractive proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A church which recognised that it had been wrong to stigmatise the children of unmarried mothers, to refuse unbaptised babies and those who had committed suicide the benefit of burial in consecrated ground; to tell the mothers of babies miscarried in pregnancy that their babies would be forever in Limbo, with all the unbaptised babies who would never see the face of God; to take babies from young unmarried mothers and send them away to adoption; which ran places like Artane and Letterfrack…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It became acceptable for us not to wear the black mantillas or hats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the excitement of Vatican II – the novelty of the priest facing the people, and the words of the Mass in English, the excitement of the sisters at my convent school as they laid aside their long black habits for conventional clothing, and began to move out of the convents to live in the community, the Vatican II documents which articulated Catholicism. There were other things too - it became acceptable for us not to wear the black mantillas or hats to cover our hair in Church. Women could enter the Sanctuary and become Readers, girls could be altar servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as in society the professions (with the exception of education), politics, medicine, accountancy, have only limited numbers of women, so the experience of women in the Church has been limited, but even more so, for ordination within the Church is reserved to men, and one of the consequences of ordination is that it brings with it the right to be a decision maker. If you can’t be ordained within our Church then you cannot ultimately be a decision maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we are asking ourselves in these changed days, in which not enough has changed for women, what has been the effect of the advent of Pope Francis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These were heralded as innovative actions, but he was not the first Pope to do things like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially he definitely gave rise to a sense of hope and expectation: he was so different from the reserved, somewhat austere and intellectual Benedict, and the charismatic, energetic John Paul II. Stories were told of how he went out in Rome at night, anxious to remain in contact with ordinary people, how he visited prisons, washed the prisoners’ feet (even women prisoners).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were heralded as innovative actions, but he was not the first Pope to do things like this - John XXIII did it, John Paul II did similar things. So did others I am sure. We have just forgotten that that is how it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is different about Francis and why do we talk about the Francis effect? Why was there such an explosion of hope? There can be no doubt that Francis is a gifted, gentle, intellectually able, humble man. The first thing that struck me when I was in Rome last December was that his shoes were quite battered, and that he had all the appearance of an elderly, burly farmer who had put the Pope’s white robes on top of his normal clothing - no white papal trousers for this man!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was very willing to give generously of himself. He was still surrounded by what seemed like hundreds of elegant monsignori, wearing the kind of glorious pink silk most women just could not afford, who took precedence over everyone there - not too much evidence of humility or engagement with those who filled St Peter’s Square. They stayed at the top of the steps while the great multitude looked up from below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know if the Church employed an image consultant I think they would have something to say about all this! It sends all the wrong images. It is so far removed from Christ who sat on a hill to speak to people. Of course there are pragmatic reasons for the way it is done - raise him up so people can see him, use audiovisual equipment to broadcast to even more people. Dress him in white so that everyone knows who the Pope is. Francis knows all this. He, and we, have to accept that some things are just necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;His talk of the smell of the sheep seemed to be slightly offensive at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly though I, and I think many other women, believe that deep within him there is something which turns away from the pomp and the ceremony, except where it is appropriate - in the liturgy where it is not pomp and ceremony but rather richness and depth of worship, some thing very different. His talk of the smell of the sheep seemed to be slightly offensive at first.  It is not seemly to suggest that we smell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there was a much more profound sentiment behind it and what he was saying, I think, was that bishops and priests need to be with their flocks experiencing life as they experience it, not isolated and grand. I think that we cannot expect too much change too quickly though - turning around the great ship that is the institutional church will not be easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have to recognise that for change to be effective, you have to bring people with you and in the case of the Catholic Church that is 1214m people, and that has to be done once you have discerned what is the right thing to do, taking into account the whole environment, scriptural, cultural, etc within which the Church operates. That is what leadership is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also about personal example. There is nothing so powerful as seeing someone live what they proclaim They say that this is how the early Church grew. Some say also that this is why we are losing so many young people: because they look and see and hear an institution which says one thing and too often does another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that made my heart warm about Francis was hearing that he can and did cook. He refused to move into the papal apartments preferring to live in the Domus Sanctae Martha, portrayed by some of the media as a form of accommodation similar to a student hostel. Actually it is quite comfortable, even quite grand when you look at the pictures on the web, but at least he is sitting down and having his dinners with ordinary people. He has made clear from the beginning that he does not want to be isolated in the Vatican. It almost seems to me that he fears what such isolation might do to his humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is reported in the Wall Street Journal as having said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I don’t like this mythology of Pope Francis. It seems offensive to me to depict the pope as some sort of superman or a kind of star. The pope is a man who laughs, cries, sleeps soundly at night and has friends just like anyone else. A normal person.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year in Ballymena, the parish in which I live, the Parish Priest, Fr Paddy Delargy, asked us to run a seminar on a Saturday afternoon on ‘Women in the Church’. It was very well attended by well over 100 people, from all walks of life, from as far afield as Dublin and Dundalk. You have to be dedicated to give up a glorious Saturday afternoon to sit in our undoubtedly beautiful Parish centre and listen to a series of talks, engage in discussion and report back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing for the seminar, engaging with the speaker, we had tried to identify the issues which might arise, the things that mattered for women in the Church today. The media has a number of areas of focus when it thinks of women in the Church, and they are very proper areas of focus. One of them is women and priesthood, a matter to which I will return. However, although it is an issue which is regularly raised at conferences and talks, (sometimes there is an assumption that because I am prepared to speak about the word of God and about being a Catholic, I must harbour secret dreams of ordination! I don’t. I never have. Though I must confess that I was somewhat taken by the idea articulated in one newspaper that I should be made a Cardinal. I felt a certain, possibly malicious, fleeting pleasure in contemplating the concern and confusion which might ensue…!) but that is not the issue, and from my experience the ordination of women is not the primary issue for women in the Church today, important though it is. Perhaps it is as well that this seems to be the case: Francis seems to have stated quite clearly &lt;strong&gt;“not in my pontificate.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is much about this man and his living of the faith which gives heart to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Evangelii Gaudium, para 103 he stated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Church acknowledges the indispensable contribution which women make to society through the sensitivity, intuition and other distinctive skill sets which they, more than men, tend to possess. I think, for example, of the special concern which women show to others, which finds a particular, even if not exclusive, expression in motherhood. I readily acknowledge that many women share pastoral responsibilities with priests, helping to guide people, families and groups and offering new contributions to theological reflection. But we need to create still broader opportunities for a more incisive female presence in the Church. Because “the feminine genius is needed in all expressions in the life of society, the presence of women must also be guaranteed in the workplace”[72] and in the various other settings where important decisions are made, both in the Church and in social structures.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very different interpretation of how women interact with the Church than that which we have known in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More informally he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The presence and the role of women in the life and mission of the Church, although not linked to the ministerial priesthood, remain absolutely necessary and irreplaceable. As the Declaration Inter Insigniores points out, ‘The Church desires that Christian women should become fully aware of the greatness of their mission: today their role is of capital importance both for the renewal and humanization of society and for the rediscovery by believers of the true face of the Church.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What else has he done or said?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He undoubtedly focusses on women’s caring role within family, church and society, talking of how families benefit from women’s &lt;strong&gt;“gifts of delicateness, special sensitivity and tenderness”;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pope Francis encourages breastfeeding in Sistine Chapel;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He seems to be moving to bring more women into roles within the Vatican and the pontifical bodies. This will inevitably be slow work. Membership of such bodies normally lasts for several years so appointments are not made frequently. One would wonder also whether the Presidents have a strong role in the decision making. Traditionally these roles are overwhelmingly held by men, ordained and unordained&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He increased the number of women on the International Theological Commission from two to five, making them 16% of the Commission;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A body tasked with carrying out a detailed inquiry into the Vatican’s administration is made up of seven lay people, including a woman;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pontifical Commission for the Protection of Minors, (established last year to deal with sexual abuse and related issues) includes five women - and just one cardinal. The women include Marie Collins, described by French journalist Jean-Louis de la Vaissiere, as an &lt;strong&gt;“eye-opening appointment”&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just a couple of weeks ago for the first time a woman was appointed as a member of a Vatican Congregation: the Congregation for the Evangelisation of Peoples, in Rome. She is the Superior General of the Combonian Missionary Sisters, Sister Luzia Premoli;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Vatican’s Congregation for Catholic Education recently appointed a woman Franciscan Sr. Mary Melone, to lead one of Rome’s seven pontifical universities, the Pontifical University Antonianum;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pontifical Council for the Laity has 24 lay members of whom 11 are women;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pontifical Council for the Family has a Presidential Committee composed of 15 cardinals and 12 archbishops and bishops, plus 18 married couples from all over the world;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pontifical Council for Justice and Peace has a Cardinal President who is assisted by a Bishop Secretary and a woman Under-Secretary;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Pontifical Council for Culture consists of 21 Cardinals and 14 Archbishops and bishops. It also has Men of Culture but no women of culture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most congregations, councils, commissions, universities have no women members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps they should introduce some targets for women’s membership to focus minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However the Pope’s new Council of eight cardinals is led by Cardinal Oscar Andres Rodriguez Maradiaga of Honduras, to reform the Curia, who has said he was backing more posts for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to address women’s issues, the Vatican’s daily newspaper L’Osservatore Romano has launched a women’s supplement. I am not sure about that one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe things are changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most women, however, will never be in a Vatican Commission. They will not even be in a National Commission. A few hold positions in diocesan commissions. But the vast majority of the Catholic Church’s 600,000,000 women will never work outside their own parishes, and for many of them even parish opportunities are limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the work of a Catholic woman does not necessarily have to be done within the organisational structure of the Church. The Church lives in society and it is in society that most of us can make choices about how we live our Catholicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I move on to speak about that, I want to say a more general word about membership of the Church in the world and about how the church itself functions. Being of the Catholic Church, we are often told, is as being of a family. Pope Francis spoke about being of family in February this year. A healthy family life, he has said, requires frequent use of three phrases: “&lt;strong&gt;May I?&lt;/strong&gt;” “&lt;strong&gt;Thank you&lt;/strong&gt;” and “&lt;strong&gt;I am sorry.&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It might be legitimate to suggest that some of the difficulties which the Church faces today would not have arisen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this relevant to my topic today? It is because the Church is the family of God. As I have said, women over the centuries, and indeed many men, clerical religious and lay, have suffered at the hands of those in power in the Church. Decisions have been made, policies articulated, decrees issued, things have not been done which should be done, and I think it might be legitimate to suggest that some of the difficulties which the Church faces today would not have arisen had there been a consciousness of what Pope Francis has said: that permission may be necessary, that gratitude and sorrow should be expressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do think he missed one thing though. I think for a family and indeed a Church to be healthy there needs to be constant reiteration and articulation of the words “&lt;strong&gt;I love you.&lt;/strong&gt;” John Paul II was very good at using those words, for example how many of us remember, “&lt;strong&gt;Young people of Ireland I love you.&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that articulated love has to inform all that is said and done. Where it does not, dysfunction develops, and worse. To say this is not to say that there must always be consensus before a decision can be made, but it does require that there be proper consideration of all aspects and contexts within which any decision is taken or action done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of us who are parents, or carers, or guardians, or even in the presence of small children, know that on occasion the safety of the family requires that immediate action is taken, one does not debate with a small child the wisdom of inserting a screw driver into an electrical socket, for example, before removing the screw driver!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These are the things we must do to enable them to grow in safety and security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly with teenagers, one will have to enforce certain minimum requirements of them: that they get up at a reasonable hour, that they go to school, that they acknowledge that every other person whom they meet is equally important. These are the things we must do to enable them to grow in safety and security. But there comes a time when we must let them go and allow them to make their own decisions. If that is not done, if they are ignored, patronised, ridiculed, marginalised, they may fight, but eventually they may just walk away. And I think that all that applies in the context of the nourishing of the individual relationship of each of us with the God who made us, by the Church to which we belong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my thesis today is that fundamental to being a woman in the Church is faith, and an understanding of what the Church is, not an institutional monolith, but rather the body of Christ here on earth. Starting from that point has the potential to change the perceived reality - Pope Francis has said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“To understand Christ we must bear the cross. Faith is not a light which scatters all our darkness, but a lamp which guides our steps in the night and suffices for the journey. To those who suffer, God does not provide arguments which explain everything, rather his response is that of an accompanying presence, a history of goodness which touches every story of suffering and opens up a ray of light”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Lumen Fidei 20.06.13&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is both challenging and reassuring, indicating that even the Pope is aware and experiences the questioning and even doubt which all of us probably experience at times. It is also a statement of faith. Pope Benedict made a similar statement in his final audience on 29 February, 2013, saying of his papacy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Lord has given us many days of sunshine and gentle breezes, days in which the catch has been abundant; [then[ there have been times when the seas were rough and the wind against us, as in the whole history of the Church it has ever been, - and the Lord seemed to sleep. I always knew that the Lord is in the barque, that the barque of the Church is not mine, not hrs, but His - and He shall not let her sink It is He who steers her, to be sure he does so through men of His choosing, for he desired that it be so. … my heart is filled with gratitude to God, for he never did leave me or the Church without His consolation, His light, His love.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me and for many women that is the role of the Church to which we belong - to nourish our faith, to help us in our journey home to Christ, not in a patronising way but in humility and with grace:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote this the memory of Cardinal Cahal Daly came to me. In his later years after retirement, I came to know him a little, and learned a lot in occasional conversations about this business of being “of church” Through him I came to a deeper understanding of what membership of the Church is about, and of how power and authority should be exercised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways his gentle demeanour masked a ferocious intellect and a steely purpose, all of which were put to the service of bearing witness. As an employer I was much impressed by the views of those who worked for him, who testified that, regardless of whatever errors, mistakes or negligence occurred in his office and for which they were responsible, he was never irritable or critical. He would excuse the failure with a gentle: “&lt;strong&gt;It is my fault, I did not explain clearly enough what I intended.&lt;/strong&gt;” That is a practice I have always tried to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, perhaps some small example of what it is to be a member of the family of the Church, a small example of how we can live faith in our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is in this context of the mystery of the individual relationship which each of us have with God, of the wonder and power for good in our lives that the Church of Christ can be, and of the fundamental teaching which must underlie not just what our Church does, but how it does it, that women are experiencing these early days of the pontificate of Pope Francis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is nevertheless a desire that women be experienced as true actors in the Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most women who will not be prominent on the public stage, there is nevertheless a desire that women be experienced as true actors in the Catholic Church, that their voice be heard through properly managed structures, even where there is no possibility of ordination (and there are those women who refute this - there are 124 women priests and 10 women bishops, who claim valid ordination in the Catholic Church. Even though many of them have been excommunicated, they refuse to be excommunicated and carry on professing themselves to be Catholic).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most women want women to be a visible presence in the Church and a real force for good. They want the talents and skills of women harnessed for the good of the Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope Francis has said that there must be changes to decision-making structures in the Church. The restriction of decision-making power to those who are ordained is not of the gospels, rather it is of canon law, and canon law can, and obviously should be changed to permit women a real role in decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However the Synod of Bishops on the Family will start tomorrow. They will discuss “&lt;strong&gt;The vocation and the mission of the family in the Church and in the contemporary world&lt;/strong&gt;”. Among the 191 Synod Fathers there will be 61 Cardinals, one Cardinal Patriarch, 7 Patriarchs, one major archbishop, 67 metropolitan archbishops, 47 bishops, one auxiliary bishop, 1 priest and 6 religious. There will also be 16 experts, 38 auditors and 8 fraternal delegates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cardinal Baldisseri also remarked that since this assembly will consider the theme of the family, special emphasis has been given to married couples, parents and family heads, a total of 12 persons; there is also one married couple within the group of experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not exactly reassuring. Although all these people came from families, and are of families, the people who have most experience of the living of the vocation of family in the Church are married couples. Surely there should have been space for more than one married couple among the group of experts, and for more lay involvement than the 12 persons identified. One cannot anticipate that woman’s voice will be much heard in this great Synod. What a missed opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was John Paul who said that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The presence and the role of women in the life and mission of the Church, although not linked to the ministerial priesthood, remain absolutely necessary and irreplaceable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow our Church is going to have to find ways to go beyond the rhetoric and to find real ways of giving women a real voice and a role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perhaps we need targets for the number of women members of pontifical commisions, councils, congregations etc;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a change in Canon Law to enable female engagement in Church decision making;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a very real recognition from Rome that whilst the Church in Pope Francis’ native Latin America and in Africa and parts of Eastern Europe is growing stronger, here in the West things need to change because we have a very rapidly defining number of priests and religious, and we have an equally rapid decline in the numbers of young people practising their faith;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is time for a discussion about how we could introduce women deacons, reverting to the situation at the time of St Paul;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And finally, because our Church comprises women and lay men as well as those holding institutional power, we need men and women, but especially women of courage and commitment to undertake the necessary spiritual and theological development to enable them to contribute at national and international level. There is even a shortage of women speakers on matters of faith in Ireland. Why is that? How do we women change it? There are things we can do. There are things the Church must do for and with us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pope Francis has done a huge amount in the past eighteen months. We must acknowledge what he has achieved, rejoice in the energy of this 77 year old pontiff, and try to work constructively for the more profound role for women in the Church today which he has promised.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//faith/women-church-under-francis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//faith/women-church-under-francis/</guid>
        
        
        <category>faith</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>History Repeats Itself</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-edward-m-kennedy-lecture-at-the-kennedy-summer-school&quot;&gt;The Edward M Kennedy Lecture at the Kennedy Summer School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good afternoon. I am pleased  to be here today and honoured to be asked to deliver the Edward M Kennedy Lecture. Those who have worked in and on  Northern Ireland all know the contribution which he made to the work of peace, the energy and dedication to the cause of peace, the open door when we were in the US, the support for those who ploughed often lonely furrows as we tried to make a contribution to the making of the peace.  He was a warm, welcoming, generous and good man, and it is right that we remember his contribution to our peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth and reconciliation are the foundations upon which trust can grow, and from trust can emerge a society which is truly democratic, in which the rule of law exists and is respected and real, in which there is peace.  We have been seeking peace in Ireland north and south for centuries.  We are probably most familiar now with the Troubles which beset Ireland, and particularly Northern Ireland, in the past decades.  It is in that context that I have been asked to speak today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in the Republic of Ireland some 116 people died during the Troubles. In the years since 1969 there have been over 3600 terrorist related murders in Northern Ireland. We have a population of 1.81 million. To put this into context for our American visitors, if those murders had occurred in the same proportion in the City of New York, there would have been, over the 38 years, some 36,000 murders.  There have been some 50,000 injuries as a consequence of the security situation here over the thirty eight years. Were that level of injury to have been replicated in the City of New York, there would have been over 500,000 injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Had New York City suffered a similar level of bereavement, injury and trauma, the number of those affected would have been in excess of 5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Victims Commission estimated that the conflict resulted in 500,000 ‘victims’ in Northern Ireland,it defines ‘victims’ as those who are directly affected by ‘bereavement’, ‘physical injury’ or ‘trauma’ as a result of the conflict. Had New York City suffered a similar level of bereavement, injury and trauma, the number of those affected would have been in excess of 5 million. This gives you some idea of the scale of the conflict which has been the object of attempts to secure a lasting peace which continued over decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has been achieved.  We had ceasefires, disarmament, decommissioning, prisoner release, the establishment of the NI Assembly, the devolution of legislative power to that Assembly, most recently the devolution of power over matters of justice and policing, though it is not complete devolution.  The UK has retained its control over matters affecting its national security.  The past keeps coming up though. Just last week  the question of whether there could be an inquest into one of the incidents of the Troubles, the death of eight IRA men in Loughgall in 1987, killed by the SAS while trying to blow up a police station has been raised again. Two civilians who were in the wrong place at the wrong time  were also shot by the SAS.  One of them, Anthony Hughes, died.  His brother Oliver was seriously wounded The UK Government has announced that the decision as to whether there can be an inquest, will be made by the Advocate General, who is also the UK Attorney General. He is a Tory politician, Jeremy Wright MP.  The NI Attorney General, John Larkin had requested the inquests after the European court of human rights in Strasbourg found the men’s rights had been violated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an extent to which the Government’s fears in the Loughgall case, which have led to this action are reflective of so much that is part of our history.  It is possible that in the Loughgall case the fear is that during an inquest the identities of those who provided the information which enabled the RUC and the SAS to mount their ambush of the IRA men, and SAS methodologies will be revealed. It is the tension between fear of the consequences of revealing the truth, and the needs of the families of those who died, and of society as a whole,  which is at the heart of today’s debates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we cannot face the truth, can we secure that reconciliation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cases such as this, and there are many of them, the dilemmas faced by societies emerging from conflict are stark. As we look towards truth and reconciliation as the foundations for peace, we have to ask whether we can afford truth if we seek reconciliation; whether reconciliation which is not based on truth is truly reconciliation, or merely a papering over the cracks. If we cannot face the truth, can we secure that reconciliation which must be the basis of a sustainable peace?  As we look at the history of our country, as we contemplate the pain and suffering of the bereaved of the Troubles, the agony of the families of the Disappeared, the ongoing activities of both republican and loyalist paramilitaries, and their effect on our capacity to function as a people, to attract inward investment and to consolidate the peace, the question must surely be, “Can we afford not to?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the great American poet Maya Angelou said, “History, despite its wrenching pain, cannot be unlived, but if faced with courage, need not be lived again.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is truth? One of the very clear issues is that some people fear truth. There is confusion and lack of understanding about what is entailed in truth and reconciliation. Often it seems to me that we do not know what is involved and what the cost is. It is important to distinguish them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truth for today’s purpose, I think is the articulation of that which can be established as fact. People have different understandings of what truth is - for example, if we think about some of the situations of the Troubles in which IRA men have died at the hands of the British security forces - such as the Shoot to Kill cases, there are those who would argue that those deaths occurred because the British had no option but to shoot the men dead. There are others who argue that there was no need to shoot them dead, even if they were involved in terrorist acts, that they should have been arrested and processed through the courts. What emerges as a consequence of scrupulous objective independent investigation can be evidenced when it is articulated, and hence can be described as the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;7116 people applied for amnesty in return for telling their story. Only 1176 got their amnesty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This causes fear - fear, for example that if we investigate all these cases we will have to face some very difficult realities which may separate us still further. Conflict, on the scale on which we experienced it is always very messy. And so there are fears, expectations even, that what might emerge from some form of truth telling process, be it through investigation or through hearings such as those conducted by the South African Truth Commission, will be damaging, will contradict the received wisdom in each of the communities, will not be ‘the whole truth.”  In the case of South Africa where 7116 people applied for amnesty in return for telling their story, only 1176 got their amnesty, even in those cases it is said that there were people who having been granted amnesty did not tell the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet there are so many people here who have suffered grievously during the Troubles, and who need to know what happened and why. The truth is never simple. We know that the security forces infiltrated the paramilitary organisations.  We know that some of those who became agents of the state were allowed to continue to commit the most serious crimes, and that collusion was a fact of life in Northern Ireland.  I have seen it in the case of republican paramilitaries, and also loyalists. I am currently engaged in monitoring a police investigation called Operation Stafford which emerged from one of my Police Ombudsman investigations where we identified a cohort of senior UVF men who were suspected, had even admitted a number of murders and were allowed to carry on, not subject to the law, committing endless serious crimes of murder, attempted murder, extortion, kidnapping, GBH, drug smuggling etc etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that both loyalist and republican paramilitaries were involved in serious crime affecting their own communities.  Many of the IRA attacks caused the deaths  of ordinary Catholic men, women and children  The IRA abducted and murdered people whom they suspected to be informants, people like mother of ten Jean McConville, seized and taken away from her children, the youngest twins aged 6, and never seen again by them.  They told the children that she had run away with a British soldier, and for nearly 30 years they denied any role in her death.  Yet they finally admitted that they shot her dead, one lonely night by a beach in County Louth.  It can be very hard for people to admit the truth, to acknowledge the truth, even to learn the truth, when it is a truth which they find so difficult to accept.  So truth is not easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It needs trust and trust has been absent from our society&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reconciliation, I think is a process which looks outward and forward and which brings together elements which belong together, but which have been torn apart. In our Church sense we talk about reconciliation as being the process of acknowledgement of wrong doing, of repentance, of a commitment to make reparation and a desire never to be separated again, and of forgiveness. That process can apply to society. It needs trust and trust has been absent from our society, and from so many others which have been in conflict for decades. Reconciliation is about not letting the past dictate the future. It is about bringing together the goodness of all the disparate parts of our divided community and working on those foundations, rather than allowing the evil of the past to separate us in the future, as it has divided us in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also in this agenda the concept of healing. I think it is a process which is personal and inward looking. It is of the soul and the mind and the body. Healing is the balm for the soul, the mending of the broken, the fusing of the shattered, the making whole of that which was torn and shattered. I do not believe that societies heal. I believe that they may be reconciled, but it is the wounds and pains of individuals which can be healed. And sometimes it is through truth that people are finally healed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the unfinished business will continue to echo through our days&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these things must come together to create a functional society.  If we do not allow truth, if we resist reconciliation, the trauma and anguish, the unfinished business will continue to echo through our days, until eventually we are forced to deal with them. And the suspicions and distrust which run through our society, reaching to the very highest levels  will continue to undermine our fragile peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely there is a very significant role for the churches here, particularly the Christian Churches. They share  a common understanding of the call to goodness, of the need to love one another as we have been loved by God, of the need to make the call to see one another as brothers and sisters real. Could we have a year for peace, when all our churches, all our clergymen, all our people would make a really concerted effort to set together, to be together, to acknowledge that the other is my brother or sister in Christ , and that that is what really matters. I do not think that we are capable of it. Yet I know that this is what those who profess belief in Christ are actually called to, and it would help provide a basis of growing trust upon which we can build anew.  Part of our problem is that we still do not, as a society, understand that our Catholicism and our Protestantism do not mean that we cannot trust each other; that politicians in government could act for the common good rather than one side or the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We know from the work of peacemaking across the world, that most peace agreements break down within 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet at a critical time. But Northern Ireland seems to be always in crisis. The latest crisis results from First Minister Peter Robinson’s statement in the Belfast Telegraph that Stormont is not fit for purpose. There is no good time to do things in Northern Ireland. We have lurched from crisis to crisis in the context of the Troubles, buttressed on occasion by governmental help of the fiscal kind, by time, diplomatic effort and lots of other support - British, Irish and American, and also by the trading of legislative change, bringing, for example,  equality and a degree of impunity for wrongdoing in exchange  for decommissioning, for ceasefires and for peace. Thus is peace made. It is not an easy business; it inevitably requires compromise by all parties; it takes time; it can break down. We know from the work of peacemaking across the world, that most peace agreements break down within 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 20 years after the IRA ceasefire, and 16 years after the Good Friday Agreement we do have peace, but it may be fragile, and we need to preserve it. The discussions at high levels of politics are about whether the Assembly can survive, or whether either the DUP or Sinn Fein or both will collapse the Assembly. These are serious discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have known for a long time that the Assembly is not functioning as it should, as an effective legislative assembly, making decisions in the interests of the whole community. We seem to be still caught in the grip of sectarianism  despite  the chuckle brothers and all that sort of thing. Our politicians could not even agree to build one new super sports stadium at the site of the Maze Prison, so we have invested heavily in Ravenhill for rugby, Windsor Park for football and in Casement Park for GAA sports.  The budgets of critical institutions of the GFA have been reduced, thereby reducing their capacity to operate. Most seriously the NI Human Rights Commission is facing budgetary cuts which may threaten its Category A status at the UN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Robinson has said our Assembly is not fit for purpose. We have known for years that it is seems incapable of dealing with issues such as education, health etc. In the three plus years of the current Assembly some 27 bills have became law. Seven of them were budget bills. The remaining 19 dealt with issues such as the licensing of pavement cafes, charges for carrier bags, rates amendments, changes to pensionable age, rates of air passenger duty. Most of the legislation is very limited and very short (many acts have fewer than a dozen clauses). In October £87m will be cut from the budget because NI has not agreed to give effect to the UK wide welfare reforms. There are more cuts to come. We can decide to continue to pay higher levels of welfare benefits than the rest of the UK, but the UK will not fund that spending and we will have to make cuts elsewhere. As a consequence our ability to fund our health, education, transport etc are compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is time for the British and Irish governments to begin to play their part again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can the Assembly survive? Are our politicians moving towards a period of direct rule, during which hard decisions will be made by British direct rule ministers so that the major parties can then return to government having avoided responsibility at the ballot box for those same hard decisions? I think we need help. I think it is time for the British and Irish governments to begin to play their part again. Our problems are their problems and their responsibilities. Devolution can achieve so much but our politicians do not seem capable of making things work in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is the root of the inability of our elected politicians to do that for which they were elected?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that it lies in sectarianism. The parties are divided on sectarian lines on so many issues. At the root of it all lie the three issues of the past, flags and parades which have divided us for so long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Haass and Megan O’Sullivan came to NI from the US in an attempt to facilitate some agreement between our politicians on these three issues. Despite many months of hard work, there was no agreement. The options for dealing with the past have been well rehearsed. The processes of criminal investigation, truth telling, storytelling, reparations, memorials are known. There are variations upon the themes which have been tried in different places, following different conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are recognising the need to provide mechanisms to enable the stories to be told&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is really nothing new in all this. Nor is there anything new in the fact that the aftermath of conflict and of wrongdoing does not go away, despite the best efforts of governments when they seek to close down what has happened. Think for a moment about the elderly Kenyans who have emerged to claim compensation from the UK government for British wrongdoing, torture, during the Mau Mau uprising or Kenya Emergency in the 1950s. The Government now seems to be moving towards settling the claim. Think about the child survivors of neglect and abuse here in Ireland north and south, and about the mothers from whom some of those children were stolen.  Most of it happened decades ago. Yet now we are recognising the need to provide mechanisms to enable the stories to be told, the realities established, in so far as that is possible, and ultimately compensation paid to those who have suffered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Northern Ireland there are difficult conversations to be had, difficult acknowledgements to be made about wrongdoing by state and non-state actors, reparations to be made for injuries suffered, and ultimately acceptance of the realities about which people still hesitate to speak, but which are manifest in cases like Bloody Sunday, in the recovery of the bodies of the Disappeared, stolen from their families, savagely murdered and secretly buried. It must happen if we are to be reconciled as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the agreements and legislation which provide the context and framework for our attempt to build peace. The Decommissioning Act provided for limited amnesty in that evidence from decommissioned weapons and munitions could not be used in criminal trials. Legislation was enacted north and south to provide a mechanism through which experts could work to recover the remains of the Disappeared: Funding has been and continues to be provided by both governments for the work of recovering the bodies. Again evidence recovered  as a consequence of information received under the Disappeared legislation, cannot be used in criminal trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It caused great pain to those who saw murderers walking free without serving their sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prisoner release was possibly the most emotive and difficult for ordinary people to deal with. That and the accompanying legislative provision (the Northern Ireland Sentences Act 1998) which provided for short sentences in respect of pre-1998 (Good Friday Agreement) incident convictions, was possibly the most emotive element of our peace process. Sentence Review Commissioners were appointed to determine eligibility for release. Only prisoners, convicted of scheduled offences and belonging to organizations on ceasefire were eligible for release, within two years of their conviction.  It caused great pain to those who saw murderers walking free without serving their sentences.  It had to be done, just as it has had to be done elsewhere. It is always a source of contention with talk of impunity, but it is a necessary part of most peace processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have the Legislative Assembly, we have the legislative framework, we have had huge resources and great generosity, particularly from Ireland and America, but we still have these intractable problems.  The reason for it can be stated absolutely clearly by quoting the words of John F Kennedy in his Address to the United Nations General Assembly (1963) over 50 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“But peace does not rest in charters and covenants alone. It lies in the hearts and minds of all people. And if it is cast out there, then no act, no pact, no treaty, no organization can hope to preserve it without the support and the wholehearted commitment of all people. So let us not rest all our hopes on parchment and on paper; let us strive to build peace, a desire for peace, a willingness to work for peace, in the hearts and minds of all our people. I believe that we can. I believe the problems of human destiny are not beyond the reach of human beings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the challenge which we face now.  Somehow we have, as a society, to find within ourselves the capacity and the willingness to build our peace. The indicators are all that this will not happen in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Governments, I believe are acutely aware of the stasis which is our current situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teresa Villiers, speaking at the BIA conference on 5 September, 2014, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“But whether it’s the mounting pressure on our policing and justice system or unrest on the streets, the last two years have shown beyond doubt the power the three legacy issues have come back to bite us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minister Flanagan, who is here with us today, said that same day in London that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Irish government attaches the utmost importance to Northern Ireland and my talks with the Secretary of State will focus on how Northern Ireland’s parties can be encouraged back to the table to address outstanding issues including parades, flags, and the past.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also said at the BIA that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“For these reasons, in the months ahead and in facing current challenges, there is no viable alternative to the early resumption of political talks and the Irish Government is committed to using its influence and resources to achieve that objective.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have, too, to face the reality that our police are still fighting a battle against the remaining republican threat, and on a separate front they are fighting against the ongoing activities of loyalism. Chief Constable George Hamilton recognised the need to deal with the past, however he questions the cost of ongoing investigations to the PSNI.  He is also left with the legacy of the problems  relating to HET, identified in a very damaging HMIC report. He told the BIA on 06 September that &lt;strong&gt;“the work of HET remains on hold following the publication of last year’s challenging HMIC report following the work of Professor Patricia Lundy.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, in itself, means that money is being poured into HET to do the work which must be done but that work is &lt;strong&gt;“on hold.”&lt;/strong&gt; He went on to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The options I have around budgets have become extremely limited. Every choice I make has a consequence. If I put resources into one area of policing; I must take it from another. As Chief Constable, my immediate obligations must be to keeping people safe today. So, while we will continue to meet our legal obligations, there will now be change in how PSNI responds to the demands of the past and the pace at which we can service the demand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are hugely sensitive issues; and there is a massive risk to public confidence in policing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of diminished confidence in policing cannot be exaggerated. We saw it over the years of the Troubles, when the Republican community and then the Loyalist community lost confidence in the police and ceased to cooperate, knowing that providing information to the police, supporting them in their work could lead to a bullet in the head or worse. We all know that policing operates only with the consent of the people, but more importantly, with the support of the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot afford to allow confidence in policing to be reduced at a time when Northern Ireland is still struggling with the impact of paramilitarism, whilst simultaneously engaging in the battle against organised crime such as people trafficking, money laundering and drugs. In making statements such as &lt;strong&gt;“there will now be change in how PSNI responds to the demands of the past and the pace at which we can service the demand.”&lt;/strong&gt;, the Chief Constable is sending out a very clear message that there will be less cooperation at a time when the PSNI are being very heavily criticised for not making material available for inquests, when they have just acknowledged the Police Ombudsman’s right of access to police premises and materials, having refused to provide information until the Police Ombudsman brought legal proceedings against the Chief Constable in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst I acknowledge that the current Chief Constable moved to comply with the law  when he took office, I do wonder what the financial cost to the PSNI has been of the legal disputes about disclosure of documents to the Coroner and the Police Ombudsman? More importantly perhaps what will be the effect on those communities who see this ongoing reluctance to provide papers and information as further evidence of cover up and collusion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Flags and parades are not something which has bedevilled many of the conflicts across the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dealing with the past is an issue which affects every post-conflict society. Flags and parades are not something which has bedevilled many of the conflicts across the world.  They are inextricably linked here, in that they go to identity and particularly to unionist fears of a united Ireland, fears which may be heightened by the forthcoming Scottish referendum. There are now very few contentious parades. 4667 parades were notified in 2013-2014. Almost 90% of them passed off peacefully. Some 491 of them were regarded as sensitive. 187 were Twadell Avenue protest Parades and 54 related to the Garvaghy Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to be realistic.  We cannot afford ongoing protests such as the Twadell Avenue protest - for those of you who are unaware of what is happening at Twaddle let me explain. On 12 July, 2013 the parade of Orangemen and bands were banned by the Parades Commission from parading past the adjacent nationalist Ardoyne on their way home from traditional Twelfth of July commemorations. Since then they have occupied an area of land in protest. Policing this situation cost £9m to May 2014. The costs must now be in the order of at least £12m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We could have employed in the order of 500 additional nurses in our hospitals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In times of scarce resources it is crazy to expect society to spend in this way. 18 years ago we had the protests at Harryville Church. They cost several millions. They lasted 79 weeks and then they stopped. Then we had the Holy Cross protests. They lasted several months and cost millions. Now we have Twaddell. It too will pass. We could have employed in the order of 500 additional nurses in our hospitals had the Twadell money been utilised there! Which would the people of Northern Ireland really prefer, the Twadell protests or 500 extra nurses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parading occupies less of our focus now, and in a context of respect for the areas which are contentious, much has been achieved. So there is great hope that more could be done if people in authority would disregard the fear of being seen to act against their own, and to commend different approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flags on lampposts are a lesser problem, but we have had serious trouble around the flags issue generally. We see tricolours and Palestinian flags, union flags and Israeli flags, and all the loyalist paramilitary flags flying. There is a market in developing new flags which demonstrate identity. There is no doubt that the presence of tribal flags has a depressive effect on the value of property in the communities within which they are displayed. For most people, though they might not dare to say it, the raggy Union flags flying from lampposts surely cannot be symbols of loyalty to the Crown?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need changes of hearts and minds. We need, in the words of JFK to &lt;strong&gt;“strive to build peace, a desire for peace, a willingness to work for peace, in the hearts and minds of all our people.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work can only be incremental – there is something around this process of mindset that is very difficult to change. Trust is the key to all relationships, and that trust is the product of both knowledge and understanding – when people know the other and understand the other, they see the other no longer as the other but rather as another person who shares their world. When the person shares their world they cease to be such a threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;She must have destroyed his street cred but she was a brave woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years I have watched the changing of minds and hearts – I have seen people who were once sworn enemies sitting in the same room telling what has happened to them and then working out a way of working together for a better community. In Harryville, during the protests I saw a brave mother, all of 5 feet tall take the arm of her six foot tall teenage son and drag him away from the protest. She must have destroyed his street cred but she was a brave woman. I have watched leading republicans protect British soldiers from attack during rioting. We seem to have seen the end of those relentless summers of riot and destruction. Now children play more in summer and rioting is not the inevitable occurrence which they must face. We do not see soldiers on our streets. But we still have paramilitary violence and we still have too much sectarianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember being with a group of about 200 people once at a very difficult time in a particular area and after lengthy discussions a woman said to me “You don’t understand.” So I told her that I was there to understand and invited her to explain and she told me &lt;strong&gt;“The only good Taig is a dead Taig”&lt;/strong&gt; It was a shocking moment, but we were able to get through it and the meeting was not lost, indeed it was fruitful at the end of the day. As Albert Einstein famously remarked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Peace cannot be kept by force. It can only be achieved by understanding.”
     
We have come now to a place and a time when some people can very often carefully and respectfully meet and talk about these things, to enable the understanding which will allow us to embed peace in our society. We can work together to improve our environment. There are those who are trying now to dismantle the peace walls, rather than build more – but only when those who live within the shadow of their protection want them to be dismantled, because we want our people to feel as safe as they can. We want them to have jobs and training and hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is work in which wounds have been opened, and people have known again the pain of their anguish, but sometimes the opening of the wound brings with it healing and healing enables the person to move forward, and so, slowly, slowly we move to real peace. The external media has largely lost interest in Northern Ireland – there is no longer the steady flow of atrocities to report on, the vicious attacks by one group on the other. And so they have largely gone. Most of the real work of reconciliation is the work done, away from the TV cameras, by ordinary people,  in community centres and leisure centres – it is the work of healing, and it is the work which will enable reconciliation. That is the work of every citizen of this island of Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work of changing the hearts and minds of men, is very slow, very hard work. It is the work that will really copper-fasten our peace. Franklin D Roosevelt once said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If civilisation is to survive, we must cultivate the science of human relationships – the ability of all peoples, of all kinds, to live together in the same world at peace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge for Northern Ireland is to find a way to deal with the past so as to enable the present and the future. Any solution must be fully compliant with the Rule of Law and all national and international obligations. Only then can we build a future for our children and their children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a single legacy commission to do that. Eames Bradley recommended it. The arguments are conclusive. At present we have a multi-agency approach to the cases involving the Police Ombudsman, the PSNI and its HET and finally the Coroner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The duplication resulting from the current arrangements can be stated very succinctly. Investigations move from one organisation to the other. They may start with HET, or the Police Ombudsman where there are allegations of police misconduct, they may then move from HET to the PSNI or to the Police Ombudsman, from the Police Ombudsman to the PSNI, from the Police Ombudsman to the HET, from the PSNI to the Police Ombudsman and at the end of the day, as is currently the case involving the investigation of UVF/ police wrongdoing, the PSNI and the Police Ombudsman may end up simultaneously investigating the same case from different perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences are obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each time one of the investigative bodies embarks on an investigation, it must first review and where necessary re-investigate any previous investigation. This means that there is significant waste of resources as the same tasks are undertaken repeatedly by different organisations.  There are strict rules in relation to investigations which require the protection of the rights of accused persons. If the Police Ombudsman is investigating he must protect the rights of any accused or suspected police officer. He must also treat witnesses, police and non-police, in accordance with the law. A person may be a witness for PONI, and simultaneously a suspect for the PSNI, since only the PSNI can investigate civilians, the military etc. This will inevitably lead to complications as the Police Ombudsman, investigating a case in which a police officer is alleged to have colluded in criminal activity with, for example a paramilitary, cannot take evidence as to that paramilitary’s criminal activity, but must instead report it to the PSNI for them to investigate. As such cases move towards prosecution there will be the most difficult of challenges in dealing with disclosure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly the PSNI will have to treat current and former police officers, under investigation by the Police Ombudsman as witnesses, rather than as suspects, even though they are suspected of wrongdoing. If PSNI becomes aware of grounds to suspect particular types of wrongdoing by police officers they must refer the officers to the Police Ombudsman for investigation.  The waste of resources involved in all this is palpable. Investigation is a very expensive process.  To have all this repeated unnecessary investigative work is to waste tens of thousands of pounds each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; We need one totally independent investigative, fully empowered and fully resourced body. I will call it the Investigation Commission, to operate in accordance with all established national and international standards of investigation, with a remit to examine any Troubles related cases involving death up to 2006, the date of the St. Andrew’s Agreement, in which there is a complaint by victims, family members or where there is a reference by Government, by a Judge, by the Coroner, by the Director of Public Prosecutions or any other agreed body such as the Criminal Case Review Commission, or where the Investigation Commission itself thinks that investigation is necessary in the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PSNI would cease to investigate any case involving Troubles-related deaths occurring before 2006. The HET would cease to exist. The Police Ombudsman’s historic Troubles-related investigations would cease to exist and all the work would be transferred to the new Commission. The Police Ombudsman would retain a non-Troubles-related historic investigative capacity so as not to damage confidence in that Office and in policing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Investigation Commission would have to be established in a totally transparent manner, and could be required to be accountable to Parliament in respect of cases which predates the devolution of justice, and to the NI Assembly in respect of cases which may have occurred post devolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a system would require flexibility and imaginative and co-operative working processes between the two legislative bodies, something which exists already in the context of the allocation of control over matters such as the UK’s national security interests, international human rights responsibilities, the operation of the CCRC etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accountability, transparency of working procedures and openness would be vital to the ability of the Investigation Commission to attract and maintain public confidence and trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; The Investigation Commission’s investigations would inevitably reveal linked crimes and themes such as those I identified in Operation Ballast, and my various investigations as Police Ombudsman. Given what we know thus far, these are virtually certain to reveal collusive activity, significant intelligence handling failings, failures to investigate, and many other problems. All of these should be examined and reported on by the Investigation Commission with a view to ensuring that lessons are learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There really is no money in the current budgets for this work, and it must be properly resourced. There is a fear among some politicians that we cannot afford even financially to deal with the past. But those who have been bereaved, and the people of these islands need to move this work forward, so that the truth can be told, lessons learned so that history will not repeat itself. The UK government, supported possibly by the Irish and Americans, could provide separate ring-fenced funding for such an Investigation Commission, so that the NI budget would not be adversely affected, in recognition perhaps of all that has happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are all sorts of inquiries and panels running in the UK looking at issues from our involvement in Iraq, to child abuse, to medical failings and even to individual murders such as the Daniel Morgan Independent Panel which I now chair. They do require funding, but what has happened here has left a legacy of trauma, pain, mental illness, very high suicide levels, alcohol and drug addiction, poverty and in some cases sheer hopelessness. Exceptional situations require exceptional solutions. Northern Ireland does not seem capable of creating its own solution. Could the UK, Ireland and the USA work together to help further enable our fragile peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Ban Ki-Moon said, marking the 68th anniversary of the atomic bombing of Hiroshima and later Nagasaki:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“True security is based on people’s welfare - on a thriving economy, on strong public health and education programmes, and on fundamental respect for our common humanity. Development, peace, disarmament, reconciliation and justice are not separate from security; they help to underpin it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//conflict-resolution/history-repeats-itself/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//conflict-resolution/history-repeats-itself/</guid>
        
        
        <category>conflict-resolution</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Strengthening Police Accountability in Ireland</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Good morning, Ladies and Gentlemen, I am very pleased to be here with you and to have the opportunity to contribute to this seminar. There has been extensive negative coverage over the past months in relation to policing matters in Ireland. The Minister has committed herself and the government to significant reforms to be made rapidly. Today we meet to consider how those reforms might best be effected and to contemplate the matters which must inform legislative drafting and thus secure real positive change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;International experience indicates that if policing is corrupt, inefficient, repressive, or does not comply with legal and basic human rights standards, then the people who are policed become alienated from policing, and in turn, policing becomes less effective. Resentment grows where, as happened here for example, there is evidence that speeding penalty points were removed from powerful people’s records in circumstances which did not justify their removal. Resistance grows where young people, enjoying a night out encounter the use of excessive force, rather than creative managed policing designed to minimise trouble. Lawful and Human Rights compliant policing will encourage the mass of the community to co-operate with the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-principles-which-underpin-the-northern-ireland-policing-solution&quot;&gt;The principles which underpin the Northern Ireland policing solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was asked to talk about my experiences in police accountability. It all starts with the Patten Commission, which identified a set of core principles for a policing service which the people could trust. The new Police Service should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be professional, effective and efficient;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be fair and impartial;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be free from partisan political control;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be accountable, both under the law for its actions and to the community it serves;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be representative of the society it polices;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operate within a coherent and co-operative criminal justice system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those, I think, are basic principles which should underpin the operation of policing globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In policing and security terms there must be clarity of roles between the key players and those who have oversight of them. The respective roles of the government, the parliament, the army the police, and any oversight agency must all be clear. There must be appropriate separation between them and there is work to be done to secure that separation. For the police, the delivery of professional policing services across the country must be the long term aim. It is profoundly important, because it is in the individual interactions of police officer and civilian that policing is either confirmed or discredited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;policing is most effective when it is done in cooperation with, and with the support of the community being policed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To facilitate effective policing there must be an adequate and effective intelligence process, and there must be accountability by the police for the extensive powers which they hold over people’s lives and for the systems, policies, practices and manner of policing. Police officers have powers to arrest, detain, enter homes and offices and search them, and to take away material which may be relevant to a criminal investigation. They prepare the prosecution files which inform a court in its deliberations as to the innocence or guilt of a defendant. They also have limited power to use force which is proportionate and necessary when carrying out their duties. At the end of the day policing is most effective when it is done in cooperation with, and with the support of the community being policed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-do-things-go-wrong&quot;&gt;Why do things go wrong?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When contemplating how to achieve the best possible policing and security there are a number of factors which must be taken into account, because they are the factors which will either prevent or contribute to policing and security which is consistent with the law or with the international standards. The question I want to address first is why do things go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent to which there is any political interference in policing, there will be corresponding damage to community confidence both in policing and in the wider criminal justice system. The style of leadership and the institutional culture of the police service are equally important factors. I have seen examples across the world of situations in which senior officers occupy very influential positions yet tend to spend their days contributing very little to core policing activities. That creates a management and leadership lacuna which those who are malevolently intentioned will exploit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who just don’t care will also exploit such negligence, but in a different way. They will know that failures of duty and misconduct such as excessive use of force will not be picked up, and that junior officers seeking to do what is right in the face of institutional lethargy and a culture of turning a blind eye will be unsupported. Inevitably policing will be damaged. There will be enhanced resentment and lack of trust in the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;positive statements to police officers about the duty to uphold and protect the law have a significant impact on serving officers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity of role and function is vital. The police need a clear strategy which is accepted and understood by the people.
Ethical leadership is critical for preventing policing abuses – zero tolerance approaches to wrongdoing together with apologies to members of the public by senior police commanders, and positive statements to police officers about the duty to uphold and protect the law have a significant impact on serving officers. They also serve to enhance public confidence in policing. Policing has traditionally, like many other institutions been bedevilled by a ‘never apologise, never explain’ ethos. That ethos cannot be part of modern service-led policing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where there is a culture of cover up, where officers are encouraged to protect one another from accountability for their wrong doing, there will be what is generally called a “blue wall”. I have seen it in every police service I have encountered. I was told that the blue wall would make my work as Police Ombudsman impossible. This did not happen, though we did have many struggles on the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I have read of the recent reports on Garda whistleblowers, I would be fairly sure AGS is no different from any other force. Indeed there has been strong evidence in the media and in your Oireachtas Justice and Defence Committee hearings of this kind of blue wall behaviour here recently. It is profoundly important that those who choose to act ethically and to report wrongdoing should be heard, supported, and treated with great respect, their courage recognised. The police officer who tries to report wrong, who is ignored or worse, and who subsequently goes on to blow the whistle, is the kind of person police services need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;despite all that you see in the movies it generally does not work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of training and equipment will be a very important factor. Training and regular re- training is vital to maintain professional standards in the use of equipment, as are clear police policies articulating what is permissible and lawful in the context of each piece of equipment. Officers need to understand the consequences of the use of the equipment with which they are issued. Firearms officers need to know about mis-fire, ricochet, about the dangers of firing into civilian areas and of firing at car tyres in order to stop a vehicle (despite all that you see in the movies it generally does not work and can lead to an explosion if the petrol tank is hit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At all times the aim must be to reduce the level of all forms of force used to the minimum, so as to avoid both injury, and the alienation of the civilian population. Where officers believe that there is a culture of impunity, that combined with an institutional culture which approves the use of force, often results in police wrongdoing. Where they know that there will be a reckoning this will impact down the line – even a few prosecutions and convictions can have a marked halo effect on the behaviour of colleagues. The excessive use of batons, CS Spray and tasers can lead to retaliation by people which can, in the end, result in higher levels of civilian and police injury with the consequential cost of legal actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of a clear code of ethics stating clearly what is expected of each police officer in the execution of their duty may also result in police wrongdoing. The UN Code of Conduct for Law Enforcement Officers and the UN Code of Conduct for the Use of Firearms are both based on international law and international policing instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Northern Ireland the conduct of police officers is judged firstly in terms of whether there has been a breach of the criminal law, and then whether there has been a breach of the Police Code of Ethics which derives from law, and all the international policing instruments together with the provisions of the European Convention on Human Rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an obligation on supervisors to supervise, failure so to do is a disciplinary offence. There is an obligation to report wrongdoing by a colleague. Failure to do so is a disciplinary offence. What this creates is a positive statement of what it is to be a police officer and how important ethics are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;both people and police would benefit from a clearer statement of what the public can reasonably and legally expect&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have read the Garda Declaration and the Garda Charter. They seem to be aspirational. I have studied the page on the website on Internal Affairs. It is possible that both people and police would benefit from a clearer statement of what the public can reasonably and legally expect of a Gardai, and of the circumstances in which a Gardai will be regarded as having done wrong. I know that policing is complex but I think there is scope for clearer more accessible information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, of course, essential that in the exercise of police powers there is constant and complete adherence to the Rule of Law.
The Rule of Law is an expression widely used but not necessarily widely understood, so I want to say a word about some of the features of the rule of law in the context of criminal law. There was failure to ensure observance of some of these in Northern Ireland during the Troubles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone, regardless of their position in society, is subject to the law;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The rights of individuals are determined by legal rules and not the arbitrary behaviour of authorities;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Justice must be seen to be done –there must, where possible, be openness and transparency;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The state should comply with its obligations under international law, whether in Treaty or the custom and practice governing the conduct of nations;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The state should comply with all its obligations in respect of fundamental human rights;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Judges must be independent and impartial and must make their decisions on the basis of the facts before them;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A defendant should know what he is charged with;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A defendant is innocent unless he is proved guilty and convicted in a court;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A defendant should have an opportunity to defend himself, and should where necessary receive legal aid to conduct that defence;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The prosecution should disclose to the defence, all material which might assist the defence or undermine the prosecution;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There can be no punishment unless a court decides there has been a breach of the law;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any punishment must be administered in accordance with the law.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these principles there are the protections articulated in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights: the right to life, to freedom from torture and inhuman or degrading treatment, the right to freedom of expression, privacy (&lt;a href=&quot;www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/&quot;&gt;See also Article 3, 4,5 etc. of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights 1948&lt;/a&gt;) and in the European Convention on Human Rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where suspicions emerge that those entrusted with the administration of policing and security are not compliant with the Rule of Law it will have a significant and damaging effect on all forms of stability, including economic investment. There is a very real need to understand that corruption takes many forms. It is not just the giving and receiving of bribes. There is a need, too, to know how it can develop and how destructive it is. Redressing such instability will be a long process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ni-solution&quot;&gt;The NI Solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three major acts of parliament created a new order:
1. The Northern Ireland Act 1998, which created new institutions of Government;
2. The Police (NI) Act 1998, which created a new police service and new police accountability, and: 
3. The Human Rights Act 1998, which created the Human Rights Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Police accountability developed through:
1. Accountability to parliament through parliamentary questions, inquiries etc.
2. Accountability to the law through the courts and three new structures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-northern-ireland-policing-board&quot;&gt;The Northern Ireland Policing Board&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an independent public body made up of 19 civilian political and independent members established to secure an effective, efficient and impartial police service which has the confidence of the whole community. It was established by Parliament in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2000/32/contents&quot;&gt;Police (NI) Act 2000.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its function is to call the Chief Officer to account for the way in which he exercises his powers. It cannot interfere with operational policing. It meets ten times a year, and has sub-committees which look at matters such as how the resources are used, at issues of human rights. It appoints the most senior officers, and is the disciplinary authority for those officers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As you contemplate the creation of your own Police Authority I would counsel one thing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model involves both politicians who are appointed by their parties, and independent members who apply for their position on the Board and who cannot be politicians, and such boards can &lt;a href=&quot;www.nipolicingboard.org.uk&quot;&gt;play an important role in calling police chiefs to account for the general exercise of their powers.&lt;/a&gt; The Chairman is an independent member. As you contemplate the creation of your own Police Authority I would counsel one thing, from my own experience as a former member of the Northern Ireland Police Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There may be police officers who want to keep you remote, who will overload you with paper, talk in police jargon and answer the questions they would prefer that you asked, if you do not have a comprehensicve understanding of the issues. You will need a degree of courage and the ability to challenge the uniformed ranks! The hardest challenge is working out what the right question in any specific area is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;community-and-police-safety-partnerships&quot;&gt;Community and Police Safety Partnerships&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community and Police Safety Partnerships were created to enable citizens to call their local (District) police commander to account for the way in which policing is delivered in the district. Depending on the size of the area 12 – 19 people are appointed to the Partnership, which is managed by the Policing Board. They are unpaid and meet up to ten times a year. It has seemed to me that this is a very important arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are never enough police resources, but if the local district commander and the people can agree…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the meetings the people can engage with the police to identify what they think are the most important priorities for the police in the area. There are never enough police resources, but if the local district commander and the people can agree that there will be a focus on, for example, domestic and gender based violence, on theft and on gang intimidation during a period of, for example, a year, then the District Commander is mandated not just by the President or Parliament, but also by the ordinary people in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be a very important confidence building measure for people in areas where there have been high levels of police brutality, neglect of duty etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of the Policing Board nationally, and of Community Police Safety Partnerships locally, is to address how and why policing is delivered in the way in which it is and to talk about when things go wrong, with a view to ensuring that there is no repetition of what has occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However on occasion it is the conduct of police officers themselves which can lead to problems, and a system is needed to investigate allegations of criminality and of breaches of police rules by police officers. I established and ran such a police complaints system in Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Office of the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;www.policeombudsman.org&quot;&gt;The Office of the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland&lt;/a&gt; has now been in existence since 2000. The Office which had some 140 staff operated 24 hours a day, seven days a week, to provide an independent, impartial investigation service for police complaints, which would secure the confidence of the people and of the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unlike GSOC police had no investigative function in any cases which came to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like GSOC we investigated criminal, disciplinary and human rights allegations against police officers. Unlike GSOC police had no investigative function in any cases which came to us. We did not send cases back to the police for investigation. In cost terms it is cheaper to have civilians doing criminal investigation of police officers. They are not generally paid as much and the overheads are lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money can be taken from the police budget because they will no longer have to conduct all these inquiries. So there is no argument for referring matters back to the police for investigation. Indeed to do so undermines attempts to establish the independence and the perception of the independence of the accountability organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMI, which corresponds, I think, to your Garda inspectorate, really has a function of ensuring that police policy and practice is consistent across the country and that its policies are reflective of global best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-independent-police-accountability-effective--the-basics&quot;&gt;Making independent police accountability effective – the basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compliance with the rule of law;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Independence and impartiality;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adequate powers and proper funding;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adequate and constant training;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Awareness of the risk of infiltration;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robust systems and processes;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionalism;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proper security vetting;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Capability of immediate response to incidents;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pro-active as well as reactive;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open and professional working relationships with all levels of community groups and civil society;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Easy access for people and police;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open and professional working relationships with police, army, intelligence services etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will refer to these issues in greater detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also investigated police policy and practice, statistically analysed the data which we gathered on police conduct and systems issues, and reported to Parliament, to the people and to the police. Our focus was on individual officer action and context within which problems and complaints arose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Anything which police officers do, can be done by independent investigators with proper powers and training&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent accountability may be perceived as a threat by police officers and there probably will be attempts to undermine it. It may be said that it will undermine policing itself. However, having had some experience of policing and the existing accountability arrangements in many countries across the world, I see no reason why such independent impartial accountability arrangements should not exist anywhere. Anything which police officers do, can be done by independent investigators with proper powers and training. You have such arrangements here, but GSOC is not properly empowered or resourced, nor is it properly independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The powers and controls under which we operated were contained in an extensive range of legislation, all of which can be found on the Police Ombudsman’s website - www.policeombudsman.org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our process was simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To receive complaints&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To decide how they should be dealt with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To deal with the complainant and the police To deal with any other relevant agency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To reach a conclusion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To keep the parties informed throughout&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To take necessary action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Police Ombudsman receives work from many avenues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citizen complaints;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Police Ombudsman initiated crime or conduct investigation – such as Omagh;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chief Constable referral - road traffic deaths, shooting deaths, any death where the conduct of the officer may have led to the death, deaths in custody, any firearms discharges including Tasers, AEP or baton gun discharges, other serious issues;
Northern Ireland Policing Board referral - of complaints received, especially against Chief Officers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public Prosecutor referral where the Prosecutor identifies a suspicion of police wrongdoing;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Criminal Cases Review Commission referral - case of a young man convicted of murder in a case in which police officers were alleged to have fabricated the confession evidence. We investigated this and found evidence of fabrication of evidence. His conviction was set aside. The Government has now decided to give him damages for his wrongful conviction and the years he spent in prison;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Judicial referral;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coroner’s Referral;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigation of police policy and practice;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of occasions on which firearms have been used has dropped significantly following the introduction of this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My view is that if any independent system to investigate the police is to be successful it must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be compliant with the Rule of Law;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be independent of the organisations for which it has responsibility, and I have said
publicly that I do not think that it is appropriate that serving AGS officers are
present in the office of AGS. I do not know of any other independent police
accountability organisation across the world where that is the case from Jamaica
to Hungary to Ontario, that is recognised as a non starter;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be impartial – making decisions based only on the evidence which emerges from
rigorous investigation, decisions which must be made by the Commissioners, not
Commission staff. It would be desirable that any staff are employed by GSOC or
the Police Authority so that there can be no conflicts of interest. be properly
empowered (which must include a right of access to information, intelligence,
materials and all other sources);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be properly empowered. I would say that in the case of GSOC it would mean above all that there should be a capacity to deal with any officer of any rank from Commissioner to Garda. There needs to be an express duty on the Garda Commissioner to preserve evidence, incident scenes. There should be a right of access to police premises for the purposes of investigation without notice or police or ministerial consent. Witness officers must have a duty to assist investigations of their colleagues;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have the capacity to deal with complaints effectively. Informal processes should be available for less serious complaints, to lead to rapid, appropriate resolution of the matter and institutional learning. There should be no officer veto on such processes, as there is currently. Ireland resolves only 1% of complaints informally as opposed to 27% in England and Wales. The IPCC have recently produced a report on the working of informal processes (IPCC Oversight and Confidence - Casework and Customer Service Pilot Projects 2013);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be properly funded and managed with adequate time for people to bring a complaint. I do not think 6 months is enough. Moreover there should be no possibility of criminal sanction where a complaint is not founded. It is not easy to complain against those in authority, especially the police, and the current penalties are very high and would deter people who have a genuine complaint but who fear that it may not be founded;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;invest in the best possible training with a high level of ongoing training;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be aware of the risk of infiltration by organised criminals and terrorists; it will need good security policies, will have to carry out regular security sweeps about which it will tell no-one. This is normal good housekeeping when you are in this business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have really robust systems and processes for the protection of sensitive intelligence material;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be professional, properly vetted and capable of undertaking the work to be done;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be capable of conducting investigations at the earliest possible opportunity;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be pro-active as well as reactive;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engage in close and real working relationships with community groups at all levels but most particularly at the most basic level;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be accessible to both people and police;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engage in co-operative and open professional working relationships with all the security forces – especially the police, the army and the intelligence services;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have the right to access and seize documentation or property such as police computers, guns, vehicles, phones, batons powers to secure any incident scene;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have powers to access police intelligence and data systems. This is currently the subject of legal action in the North, and has been the subject of major problems between AGS and GSOC. That is not surprising, but any democracy which seeks the security of a fully accountable police service must allow complete access. It is accorded to independent police accountability organisations across the world from England to Jamaica to Brazil;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have powers to use all necessary ancillary support e.g. forensic science, photography, medical evidence etc., where they are available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;growing-community-confidence-in-policing-through-independent-investigation&quot;&gt;Growing community confidence in policing through independent investigation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are certain minimum things which can be done to grow confidence both in policing and the accountability organisation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direct interaction with complainants;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proper complaint handling processes;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regular provision of information to complainants and police officers;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acknowledgement of operational context of policing;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Action taken against police managers if justified, not just officers on the ground;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evidence-based reporting;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recommendations to improve policing;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Openness and transparency throughout – no closed doors!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my seven years we dealt with some 21,000 investigations and 35,000 allegations. When I started there were over 13000 RUC officers plus civilian staff. Very comparable to AGS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;they had difficulty with being investigated by civilians who had full police powers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was important in devising the system to identify community and police needs of the new independent police complaints system. Police officers had been accustomed to being investigated by other police officers, and they had difficulty with being investigated by civilians who had full police powers. Civilians had very often thought that there was no point in complaining about the police because they investigated themselves. We worked to establish what it was that complainants wanted when they made complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked with the police to see what they needed of an independent investigative system.
The nature of the cases to be investigated was very varied and although the investigation had to be conducted firstly with a view to identifying police criminality, often there would be allegations of misconduct. Cases in any similar independent investigative system would involve matters such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allegations of murder and manslaughter resulting from deaths following police use of guns, police car chases, road traffic accidents involving police cars, and police failure to prevent the death of someone in police custody;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allegations of assaults, Intimidation and harassment etc;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wrongful arrest and detention;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perverting the course of justice e.g. through concealing evidence, through fabricating evidence and through giving perjured evidence in court;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Theft of property by police officers;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abuse of power - through wrongful arrest and detention, searches of property etc.;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Failure to respond to a call for assistance or to investigate following a crime;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Failure to provide a fair investigation and trial process – e.g. by not cautioning an individual, depriving him or her of a lawyer during interview, failing to ensure the continuity of evidence, not disclosing relevant evidence to a court etc.;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incivility, poor attitude and failure of communication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key minimum characteristics of an impartial, independent system for the investigation of alleged police wrong doing were identified by us as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionalism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accessibility and Confidentiality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clarity and Transparency where possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Responsiveness and Effectiveness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speed and Simplicity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accountability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often our investigation indicated that there was no wrongdoing by police – for example, the complaint of failure to respond to a call for police assistance may have been explained by the fact that all the available officers were dealing with a very serious road traffic accident. Equally, investigation of an allegation of failure to investigate may have indicated that there had been an investigation, but there had been a failure to communicate appropriately with the victim of the alleged crime. However in many cases it was clear that there were failings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When examining an officer’s conduct criminal law issues would be investigated, together with any associated disciplinary matters. For example, any force used must be only that which is absolutely necessary – someone who is unarmed and running away should not be shot if they do not represent a threat to the life of another person - other methods should be used to restrain them if detention or restraint is necessary. Similarly if a police officer has to use force to arrest or detain someone it should be only necessary force which is proportionate to the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;improving-policing-through-independent-investigation&quot;&gt;Improving policing through independent investigation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identification of training needs;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identification of systemic failings;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identification of equipment needs;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provision of management information;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consequential recommendations for improvement;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identification of policy and practice changes required.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made evidence based recommendations for the prosecution of police officers when they had to be made, and we ensured that officers were disciplined where necessary. When policing had been properly conducted we said so. When officers had acted bravely, we said so. When training was required we recommended it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Where what has gone wrong was not the fault of a junior officer but rather a failure of management or supervision we dealt with that failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the good by-products of independent investigation is that properly done it can grow community confidence in policing. Where what has gone wrong was not the fault of a junior officer but rather a failure of management or supervision we dealt with that failure. Above all it was about trying to achieve maximum openness and transparency in the police complaints system whilst simultaneously protecting the necessary procedures and practices of good policing, such as proper intelligence and informant handling and investigative techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very important part of an independent investigation system is to bring to the attention of the police systemic failings which may be leading to breaches of human rights, or other failures of professional policing, so that the systems can be changed for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training can be expensive to organise and it takes officers away from duty, but without training they will not be competent to do the job and this will damage police/people relationships. Equipment can be essential to an officer’s ability to police in accordance with international standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An independent investigation system can also be used to provide management information to the police about the extent to which equipment such as handcuffs, batons, vehicles etc are alleged to be used in abuse of force cases, and about locations of incidents, which officers are involved in alleged wrong doing, which officers attract multiple complaints etc – all of which can be used by the police, using management interventions to ensure professional policing practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;officers were not being regularly and properly trained in the use of their guns&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concern about police use of force led us to make a number of recommendations to the police about necessary action. For example, investigation demonstrated inappropriate use of police firearms leading to serious risk that someone would be killed: Some officers were not taking account of the possibilities of mis-fire, ricochet or injury to an innocent third party. Police officers were not being regularly and properly trained in the use of their guns, and particularly in the occasions on which it was lawful, necessary and proportionate to use the gun. Once proper, regular training was introduced the number of occasions on which firearms were used dropped significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were many complaints about police use of batons. Police officers in Northern Ireland were forty times more likely to be accused of abuse of force than their English colleagues. They were six times as likely to be injured. What we found on investigation was that many officers were trained in the use of force only once in their career. As a consequence bad habits could become engrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many officers did not have quick cuffs (the handcuffs which snap on) because they had not been trained to use them; they did not have Pepper or CS spray. They did not have Tasers. They were armed and had to prevent people from taking their guns from them. They did not receive conflict resolution training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the number of complaints about abuse of force dropped very significantly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When all officers had received human rights training on the necessity for the use of force to be lawful, necessary, and proportionate, and also on the use of conflict resolution techniques, and were properly equipped, the number of occasions of use of force, and the number of complaints about abuse of force dropped very significantly. Equally significantly the amounts which the police had to pay out in compensation for abuse of force dropped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this the level of police injuries dropped – police are at risk of injury when they use force, because people may retaliate; if the number of occasions on which they use force can be reduced so, in all probability, will the number of occasions on which officers are injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is said by others that independent Police Ombudsman investigations have proved to be vital in securing the confidence of the people in policing. One of the keys to effective policing is belief among the people that the police themselves keep the law, and the confidence that if the police do break the law they will be dealt with like anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These can be sensitive and difficult conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the beginning of these activities is faltering, and there is concern. On occasion I was asked to go into a community so that they could explore what cooperation with the police might look like; how they could engage; what the risks might be, and how they could be assured that the police would not abuse them or harass them. These can be sensitive and difficult conversations. Sometimes we went again into the group, with their agreement, with the police, for further meetings. These were important encounters. They might be one small factor in enabling communities to move from disconnection with the law and those charged to enforce it, into co-operation with policing dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did our people think of us? 86% believed that we were independent. 78% of the people believed that we were impartial. 84% thought we were fair. And even police officers who had been investigated and were anonymously surveyed reported high levels of
confidence – 90% of police officers, who had been investigated, believed the independent investigator was impartial, 84% believed they were fair and 92% believe they were professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independent investigation of police and security sector wrongdoing is one tool which, used in conjunction with proper leadership, management, training, equipment, resources, policies and practices can bring about much better policing and security. Positive leadership, not just warm words are necessary, on the part of all the leaders of institutions throughout the criminal justice system to accommodate the new order It can engender confidence both in the independent investigative system and in policing itself. It can be a challenge for police. In Northern Ireland the police commanders recognised the benefits of the system and the people had confidence in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent investigation can:
- Identify wrong doing and present a case for prosecution or disciplinary action;
- Identify cases where the evidence does not support the allegations and explain this clearly on an evidence based approach to the people;
- Grow confidence first in the fact that there is purpose to registering the allegation of wrongdoing and that it will be dealt with;
- Grow confidence in the community that the police, security or military are there to protect them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing independent investigation of allegations against police officers is not easy, but the benefits clearly outweigh the costs. You have a moment of opportunity now. It will be challenging and difficult. If you follow through and seize the moment Ireland will have better structures of governance overall.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//policing/strengthening-police-accountability-ireland/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//policing/strengthening-police-accountability-ireland/</guid>
        
        
        <category>policing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>St John Paul II Celebration Charity Dinner</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Good evening, Bishop McAreavey, Mr Jerome Mullen, Honorary Consul for Poland, Mayor, Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen. It is a great pleasure and a great honour to be asks to speak to you tonight as we gather to celebrate the canonisation of Karol Wojtyla, the little son of Poland who grew up to become Pope, a man of whom Poland and her people can justly be so very proud, and a man who became so much loved across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a few years Declan and I went to Krakow on holiday. it was a wonderful experience, marred for me only by the visit to Auschwitz which had to be done: one cannot in conscience turn away from the pain of others because it is too painful to bear. And so we went to Auschwitz. But on the way home, we caught a little local bus, then another little local bus to Wadowice- Declan is very good at sorting things out, but I did not think we could possibly get to Wadowice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t speak Polish, there wasn’t much in the way of tourist guides at that time. But we got there and it was a lovely experience to walk the roads that the little Karol walked, to enter the Church where he lived his young years, to visit his home so close to the Church and to see the exhibition of things from his early childhood, his skis, if I remember correctly, then the magnificent episcopal robes which he once wore. I think it gives a tiny insight into what formed the man whose life we celebrate today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;a sheer and exuberant love of God’s world and God’s people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saints are ordinary people, and there can be no doubt that, no matter how extraordinary he seems to have become, he was just one of the people. He lived an ordinary life, came from an ordinary family, though that was to change more than anyone could have anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we seek to understand his sainthood we must think about the young Karol Wojtyla - his early years, so touched by tragedy, his later years so challenging and accompanied throughout by so much pain, and yet through all that so much of poetry, drama, philosophy, sport and what seemed to me a sheer and exuberant love of God’s world and God’s people. It was an extraordinary life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who come to sainthood often have significant experience of suffering. Karol Wojtyla was such a man. I have often pondered upon some of life’s apparent unfairness, and wondered on occasion why some people seem to suffer so much. The young Karol Wojtyla is one about whom I have wondered. The death, before his birth, of the older sister he might have had, then the loss of his mother when he was just nine years old, an age when little boys are striving to become men; it must have been a terrible loss. Mothers are there to love their sons, to affirm them and to be gentle for them in trying to guide them along the right path. This little boy lost his mother at a very tender age and he must have been bewildered at her loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years later he wrote this poem. faith:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Over this, your white grave&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;the flowers of life in white–&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;so many years without you–&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;how many have passed out of sight?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It speaks for itself with such love and&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Over this your white grave&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;covered for years, there is a stir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;in the air, something uplifting&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;and, like death, beyond comprehension.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Over this your white grave&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;oh, mother, can such loving cease?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;for all his filial adoration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a prayer:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Give her eternal peace—&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had a great devotion to Mary, the mother of Jesus. As the third of three children, his brother much older than him, and as the son of a man who was by all accounts a loving but very Spartan father, Karol seems to have learned early the lessons of self-sufficiency and independence. He suffered also the loss of that older brother, the doctor who died too young of illness contracted from his patients, and, at the age of 20, of his father. As he himself said, “At twenty, I had already lost all the people I loved.” There is a deep sadness in that statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He once wrote about what the importance of Mary - he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“From Mary we learn to surrender to God’s Will in all things. From Mary we learn to trust even when all hope seems gone. From Mary we learn to love Christ her Son and the Son of God!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That could only be written by someone who had really known suffering and darkness, yet who was carried through it by faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is talked of as a man who was never without his rosary beads, who prayed whenever he had the opportunity. There are stories of him praying all night when faced with particular challenges. The constancy with which a man can pray all through the night is something to be marvelled at. I don’t know many people who do that do you? This was man who lived so closely to God. That is why he is a saint today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He who visited many shrines to Mary - Guadalupe, Jasna Gora, Loreto, Lourdes, Knock, Fatima and others, and he said that she saved him when Mehmet Ali Agca tried to kill him in St Peter’s Square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He spoke of her role in protecting the Church in the first book of his which I read, “Sign of Contradiction”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Precisely in periods when Christ, and therefore his Church, Pope, bishops, priests, religious and all the faithful become became the sign which provokes the most implacable and premeditated contradiction, Mary appears particularly close to the Church, because the Church is always in a way her Christ, first the Christ-child and then the crucified and risen Christ.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking in Knock on his visit to Ireland he talked of how very little is recorded in the Gospels of what Mary said. He pointed out that at Cana she had said to the servants “Do whatever he tells you.” He told us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This same message she still speaks to us today.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In speaking to the sick he told them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“remember that Our Blessed Mother, Mary, is close to you, just as she was close to Jesus at the foot of the cross. And she will never leave you alone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has often seemed to me that these very simple messages were the messages that his own mother must have given him on many occasions. For this is what he seems to have done as young man, priest, bishop, archbishop, cardinal and Pope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst much has been written of his poetry and his love for philosophy and drama, of the mountaineering, the canoeing trips and the sport, the years of his university education and his seminary formation were also very tough years. It seems amazing now that a man who worked in the stone quarry would one day occupy the throne of Peter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wrote a poem about what it was like in the quarry, about the blasting of the stone, the hardness of the rock, the dust and the mud, It is about the death of a fellow worker. Listen carefully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He wasn’t alone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;His muscles grew into the flesh of the crowd, energy their pulse,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;As long as they held a hammer, as long as his feet felt the ground.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And a stone smashed his temples and cut through his heart’s chamber.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;They took his body and walked in a silent line&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Toil still lingered about him, a sense of wrong.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;They wore gray blouses, boots ankle-deep in mud.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In this, they showed the end.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;How violently his time halted: the pointers on the low voltage dials jerked, then dropped to zero again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;White stone now within him, eating into his being,taking over enough of him to turn him into stone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Who will lift up that stone, unfurl his thoughts again under the cracked temples?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But the man has taken with him the world’s inner structure,where the greater the anger, the higher the explosion of love.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political environment in which he came to maturity and to ordination was so very tough. He fought communism and materialism. He is credited internationally with having contributed much to the end of Communism. He constantly asserted the right to freedom, recognising that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Freedom consists not in doing what we like, but in having the right to do what we ought.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He asserted the right to life in so many spheres, not just abortion and euthanasia. He had a number of serious accidents and as Pope he was nearly assassinated, finally succumbed to the crippling arthritis and to Parkinson’s Disease. He seemed to bear it all with a fortitude and grace, and with humour and love. He was, above all, a man who believed the words of Jesus: &lt;em&gt;“Be not afraid.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 263rd successor to St Peter was, in some ways, an unlikely character. Although he held the titles of bishop, archbishop and cardinal when he became pope, he was not known in the world as some candidates for the papacy have been. When he died he was probably the most widely known person in the world. He strode the world’s stage with grace and constant compassion. As a younger pope he was very fit and continued to engage in various sporting activities. When he became old he was almost unrecognisable as the fit young man he had once been. His achievements are legendary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His twenty-six years as Pope encompassed the greatest period of change in the Catholic Church for centuries. His greatest call, I think, was the call to each of us to recognise that we are called to holiness and to understand and live that call. I never met the man. I stood in Phoenix Park with Declan on 29 September I979 with a million and a quarter other people and saw him from a huge distance. I would dearly have liked to have met this man who came through so much, and who in his living and in his dying lived the Gospel in a way which touched the souls of so many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me the most compelling thing about Karol Wojtyla was the power and conviction with which he articulated and communicated his faith in all its aspects. There were those who criticised his use of the media, for example, when he went to visit in prison the man who tried to murder him, he did not go without the cameras. He once said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The question confronting the Church today is not any longer whether the man in the street can grasp a religious message, but how to employ the communications media so as to let him have the full impact of the Gospel message.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a scene so reminiscent to all Catholics of a confessional scene, he was shown sitting leaning forward and listening attentively to Ali Agca. What it said to us all was that the Pope had forgiven the man who tried to murder him and wanted him to know that. For all those who have suffered at the hands of others it was an example of how we should forgive as we are forgiven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His compassion which seemed obvious to me, showed also that forgiveness is not just a giving up of anger and bitterness at the harm caused, but it can also be a reaching out to those who have harmed us in the most terrible ways. I remember watching him and thinking this is real Christianity. I could only see this and learn from it because he took the cameras with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years previously I had lost in pregnancy a much-wanted first baby when I was caught in a bomb explosion. My anger at those who had denied my child life was massive. As I watched the Pope forgive the man who had sought to kill him, I had much to ponder on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As John Paul II walked through the world, travelling to extraordinary places, especially places of great conflict or deprivation, from Northern Ireland to Cuba, to Africa and India the media were always there. I said on RTE the other night that for me he was the Pope who brought the Papacy and the Vatican to Ireland, where previously it had been a distant place and the Pope an even more distant figure, who lived in Rome, ruled the church, appeared at intervals gorgeously robed to give blessings and produced densely scripted encyclicals (and I do know there was more to it than that!), this man brought the truth of the Gospels wherever he went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He prayed and talked to ordinary people and to world leaders, and in his work he changed the world so much that there were powerful people who feared him enormously, because what he taught was the antithesis of what they sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of what John Paul II wrote has been published in dense format with very limited circulation. This is a pity for he has so much to tell us. His book “Crossing the Threshold of Hope” is different. It had wide circulation. In it the he talked of how the conscience of the peoples and nations of the world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“needs to grow in the certainty that Someone exists who holds in His hands the destiny of this passing world”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He tells us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“this Someone is Love – Love became that man, Love crucified and risen. Love unceasingly present among men. It is Eucharistic Love. It is the infinite source of communion. He alone can give the ultimate assurance when he says “”Be not afraid.””&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These words have been of great importance to me both in my professional life and as a wife and mother – there have been times when the challenge has seemed too great, and yet I have learned, as John Paul said, &lt;em&gt;“The power of Christ’s Cross and Resurrection is greater than any evil which man could or should fear.”&lt;/em&gt; We must just hold on and &lt;em&gt;“be not afraid.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure that many of you have had similar experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These words, which I first heard as a little girl, and which were so clearly articulated by this Pope who had so much cause to be afraid, have stayed with me over the years. To watch this man stride the world in his younger years, and falter slowly but not hesitatingly in his later years, was to watch living faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how much his health failed he never gave up. I was among those who thought he should have stepped down, that the world needed a younger, vigorous Pope, who would concentrate his energies on the emptying churches, the falling vocations in the west, the challenge of secularism. Yet I came to realise that he was doing all those things in his failing years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as he had modelled strength and determination and huge communication skills in his earlier years, so in his latter years he modelled for us the dignity and wisdom of age, the great love which valued all people, and the importance of knowing that we are held in Christ’s hands all of our days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in a culture in which age is not valued as it should be. In other cultures the old can be reverenced for their wisdom. That rarely happens here. And here we have the nightmare of abortion, and now the threat of euthanasia and assisted dying as mediums through which the world can be relieved of the need to look after those who are old and sick. In all he did John Paul witnessed to the sacredness of each human life, of each person made and loved by God. He said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The inalienable dignity of every human being and the rights which flow from that dignity - in the first place the right to life and the defense of life - are at the heart of the church’s message.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His testament was a testament of truth for it spoke eloquently of love and joy, and peace and patience, and goodness and all those other gifts of which we learned, but which we did not know, when we were children. It spoke perhaps most of all of the truth of the Resurrection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Paul marched across the world’s stage, a man of intellect, but above all a man of faith. he addressed all aspects of all human life in the world - politics, philosophy, science, interfaith dialogue - it was he, against the advice of many who brought 120 religious leaders together to pray and reflect on faith - who spoke so courageously against violence and war, of the need for peace, the sanctity of human life, the importance of people’s dignity - the need for each of us to contribute to the other, to live our lives not for ourselves but for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He did not fail to challenge when challenge was necessary but not easy - for example to America: Radical changes in world politics leave America with a heightened responsibility to be, for the world, an example of a genuinely free, democratic, just and humane society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of science he said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Science can purify religion from error and superstition. Religion can purify science from idolatry and false absolutes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To those who would use all ends to secure social justice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Social justice cannot be attained by violence. Violence kills what it intends to create.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his Papacy he was brave enough to try to deal with the wrongs of the past, he apologised for so much of the Church’s wrongdoing over the centuries, that he was criticised for apologising too much. He apologised for the treatment of Galileo; the Inquisition and the religious wars that followed the Protestant Reformation; some Catholics’ involvement with those responsible for the African slave trade; the wrongs done to women; the failures of many Catholics during the Holocaust, and he made the early apologies for clerical sexual abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where wrong has been done we are called to confession, contrition and reparation. That is what he was modelling as the leader of the Church which had sinned. He could have just ignored it, but his was a life lived for reconciliation and peace and justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His words in Drogheda in 1979 when he came to Ireland and pleaded for peace made an enormous impact. I remember it as if it was yesterday. He spoke of the &lt;em&gt;“inalienable rights of human beings.”&lt;/em&gt; He spoke &lt;em&gt;“in language of passionate pleading”&lt;/em&gt; to the men and women engaged in violence, telling them that &lt;em&gt;“violence only delays the day of justice. Violence destroys the work of justice”&lt;/em&gt; begging them to &lt;em&gt;“return to the ways of peace.”&lt;/em&gt; He prayed &lt;em&gt;“for peace and reconciliation, for the victory of justice and love over hatred and violence.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No saint was ever perfect. Peter denied Jesus three times, Augustine lived a wild life causing his mother to pray endlessly, as mothers everywhere do for their sons! The great St Francis too lived a life of wealth and disregard for others before he came to holiness. So it is not surprising that there are things which John Paul did and said in his time which led to controversy. Some of those things may in due course be revisited by the Church, but the essence of this man is that he lived his life for others, that he was a man of prayer and faith, that he did not spare himself in working for the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are those who say that his canonisation has come to soon - but the reality is that our world has changed so much that we know more about this man who was Karol Wojtyla than we do, probably, about any other saint. His writings are available to us, much of his life was recorded in the media. He was studied and analysed by philosophers, scientists, journalists and so many others. His cause survived the process of making him a saint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not believe it is too soon. We live in a different, more informed, more open and transparent world and it is in that world that John Paul II lived and worked. He himself made many saints, more than all the other popes in history it is said. He worked to identify ordinary men and women of great holiness and to identify them as people whose holiness we can try to emulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His holiness was there for all to see. It is not too soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Paul II was a man of heroic virtue, he struggled at times in his life, he was not perfect, we know that, but the magnitude of the spirit and soul and intellect of this great man was very clearly demonstrated by the millions across the world who came to listen to him speak, who attended his dying and who mourned at his passing. This was no ordinary man, no ordinary bishop. This was a man of God and it is wonderful that we can be together this evening and celebrate his life and his great love and compassion for the world.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//faith/john-paul-ii-celebration/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//faith/john-paul-ii-celebration/</guid>
        
        
        <category>faith</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Soroptimists International Charter Lunch</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The work of Soroptimists International across the world is profoundly important and so varied. You work, I have read, with Women Survivors of War – in partnership with Women for Women International in Afghanistan, Bosnia and Herzegovina and Rwanda, for the victims of landmines in Afghanistan, Angola and Georgia, to prevent the spread of AIDS in Thailand by giving young women occupational training and scholarships so that they do not have to enter the commercial sex trade. you contribute to building eye clinics in Bangladesh to prevent pre-school children going blind, helping the poorest women and children in the highlands of Peru and providing safe water for many villages in Senegal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital work and you can indeed be very proud of it. But you need to know just how difficult and challenging the work is on the ground. Victims of landmines do not just need prosthetic limbs. They need physiotherapists - very rare in conflicted countries. They need technical support for when the limbs break. They need wheelchairs and they need maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been asked to speak today about my experience of working with women post conflict across the world. It may be that what I will say will further develop your understanding of how women survive conflict and of they work for peace in such difficult circumstances. I have worked with women from many conflict zones in many roles but most recently as Police Ombudsman for NI, then as Ireland’s Special Envoy for Conflict Resolution, and now as a Member of the House of Lords, working particularly with women parliamentarians from conflict zones. It is privileged work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Their primary need will be for security – that is more important than food and water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many women caught in conflict work for peace long before the international peace makers arrive. In a context of seeing their children taken as child soldiers, experiencing rape being used as a tool of war, and very often being displaced to IDP camps, or even worse being forced to flee to an adjoining country as refugees, there will be those women who will fight for peace. Their primary need will be for security – that is more important than food and water – without security the long trek to collect water becomes fraught with danger of gender-based violence. Attendance at food distribution centres or working in the fields to grow their own food is similarly fraught with danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding this, women will get together in small groups and begin to try and find a way to peace. They will care for each other’s children, mind the market stalls, and share their few good clothes with those who are seek to participate in public life. They need help from the very beginning. They will develop networks which, properly utilised could form an effective basis for that community development which is fundamental to peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will also be women who played their role as combatants but who come to a place where they want to work for peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The NI structures followed the normal pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace-building is not the work of days or months. It is the work of years. The NI peace process has probably continued throughout most of the forty five years since 1969. It became overt after the IRA ceasefire in 1994, and even now we still face the threat of attack by dissident republican paramilitaries. So peace making takes a long time. The NI structures followed the normal pattern: we had decommissioning, demobilisation, resettlement, we had prisoner release, we are seeking a way of dealing with the past, we had security sector review and consequential change. We had many confidence building measures. Throughout it all women were engaged, for a long time on the periphery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the pattern of peace processes. So how do we get women involved from the beginning, and how do we enable them to play their proper part? That is the question which particularly interests me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before peace is made there will be peace-building – women must be involved from the start. The need for their participation in politics and civil society is recognised in UNSCR 1325 and the associated UN Resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is Resolution 1325 about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resolution 1325 is a United Nations Security Council Resolution about women, peace and security, which was passed in October 2000 – it highlights the need for action in 4 areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The participation of women at all levels in decision making relating to the prevention, management and resolution of conflicts;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to have gender perspectives in conflict analysis and in the training of military and civilan personnel in peace-keeping missions, including on the protection, rights and needs of women affected by conflict;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a need to ensure protection of women’s rights during conflict including prevention of and ending impunity for gender-based violence, in the context of settlements for people who have been displaced by conflict and addressing the needs of female ex-combatants;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is finally a need for gender mainstreaming in UN implementation and reporting mechanisms including reporting by by the Un Secretary General on progress towards implementation of UN SCR1325.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ten years since the Resolution was adopted by the United Nations little has happened to give effect to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four UN resolutions are expressed for the most part in language which is weak: they urge and express willingness to help, they call for and stress rather than demanding a response. There is no provision for targets or measurement, and there are no sanctions for non-compliance. Women do not have an equal voice. They are subjected to high levels of domestic violence. I have spoken to them about this. In post-conflict countries where the police, the courts and the justice system have broken down and where there is a tradition of male dominance, women are acutely vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that across the world, wherever there is violence women suffer – the loss of loved ones, children, homes, livelihood, friends, even country. Rape is acknowledged in many conflict countries to be a tool of war. Whole villages of women and children are raped by militia recognising the pressure which such action places on the international community and on national governments. I have heard terrible examples of the extent of the horror of war – I will tell you one – in one serious conflict militia seeing a young pregnant woman in the street running for safety bet on the sex of her unborn child, then they seized her, took the child from her womb to determine its sex, and then left mother and child to die where they lay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been reported that 40% of countries emerging from conflict return to war within five years. Women have a crucial role to play in building sustainable peace, and the women whom I have met all say that this cannot be done by women alone – it must be done by men and women together – as the Liberian women I worked with sang:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No longer the men at the front and the women at the back, together we will march side by side.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen many examples of such women at work, in various countries across the world in the most difficult and terrifying of circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in Timor recently I shared with some of our Timorese NGOs some of the reality through which Ireland has come over the years. There are those alive in Ireland and the UK today who remember walking to school barefoot, who remember that there was no general education for all, who remember great hunger and deprivation. My Timorese listeners had great difficulty in accepting that we had known famine, and hunger and poverty on that scale. We now have recession, but we do not have the kind of poverty with which they live. Life here is very different today from the Ireland of thirty or forty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we in Ireland share our experiences of conflict and of the transformatiom from conflict in which we are still engaged I think that we can learn today from what did happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Peace negotiations rarely have women negotiators at the heart of the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s think for a moment about how few women are involved in peace-making. Support structures are necessary, as is the recognition of the right and need for women to mobilise for peace. SRSGs have been predominately male. There is a need for active support for the development of women to play senior roles in the UN and other peace-building agencies. Peace negotiations rarely have women negotiators at the heart of the process. They may be present in a peripheral way, making the food, looking after the accommodation, but they are rarely present at the top table. It is important that we try to ensure that the peace teams which are funded have women at the highest levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace-making is a male dominated business. I attend some of the major peace-keepers’ meetings and there are few women who have experienced high level peace negotiations and processes. At these meetings as we discuss the practical implementation of UNSCR 1325, it is often said that combatants will not welcome women to the peace table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries in conflict are very often patriarchal and will have no experience of dealing with women on equal terms. The peace negotiators and all funding agencies must ensure that they put women at the heart of peace processes. Failure to do so will inevitably mean that the call for women at the table will be met with the response, &lt;strong&gt;“You have no women involved at the top.”&lt;/strong&gt; It is said that the warlords will very often refuse to allow gender issues on the table at peace negotiations from the very beginning, because this will necessarily involve such issues as reparations and judicial process against those who have used rape as a tool of war, and indeed have made it clear to those they are fighting, that this is what they are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These issues will be on the table and that there will be no peace without them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To allow issues of “no immunity” to be placed on the table, it is said, is like asking turkeys to vote for Christmas. They simply will not do it. But if the common understanding is that the United Nations and its member states have determined that these issues will be on the table and that there will be no peace without them, those who have been involved in combat and who are minded to make peace will not allow this to be an impediment. There are many factors and dynamics which encapsulate peace negotiations, some of them spoken and some unspoken. It is of course also the case that full peace negotiations normally last years and that there are many levels of peace processes, some local and some national. Each forms a building brick in the creation of the structures which will enable peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for protection from GBV is equally important though, and this is one of the factors which will liberate women to play their part. One of the problems of the presence of peace-keepers is that they can exacerbate the very problem they are sent to resolve. The problem of UN babies and the babies of employees of NGOs working in conflict zones is widely discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With conflict comes trauma and post-traumatic stress, and a sense of frustration and marginalisation among the foot soldiers of the conflict who are very often abandoned after the peace is made. Countries engaging in peace processes often think that they have bigger problems to deal with than trauma and its associated problems, and to prioritise funding for other projects. However the reality is that those suffering from trauma and PTSD etc may represent an ongoing risk of conflict as their trauma levels may mean that their response to difficult situations is predicated by their psychological suffering, and they may react with violence to situations which others could manage peacefully. In a volatile and dynamic post-conflict situation, lacking the normal processes for the rule of law, the ongoing risk to women is well documented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Liberia just a few years ago a few women came forward to lead their country into peace. There had been peace until a civil war between 1989 and 1996. This was followed by a second civil war between 1997 and 2005. It was a terrible war. Over 250,000 people died. Its population is fewer than 4 million. Those women had nothing, no money, no power, little education. Many of them were poor market traders, living in terrible conditions but motivated by the dreadful destruction of the war to give everything they could for peace. They have gained a fragile peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These women like so many women caught in conflict, had worked for peace long before the international peace makers arrived. They got together in small groups and began to try and find a way to peace. They cared for each other’s children, minded the market stalls, and even, where necessary, shared their few good clothes with those who were to participate in public life. By 2002, the women in Liberia were tired of seeing their country torn apart and started gathering and praying in a fish market to protest about the violence. They organized the Women in Peacebuilding Network (WIPNET), and issued a statement of intent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“In the past we were silent, but after being killed, raped, dehumanized, and infected with diseases, and watching our children and families destroyed, war has taught us that the future lies in saying NO to violence and YES to peace! We will not relent until peace prevails.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joined by the Liberian Muslim Women’s Organization, Christian and Muslim women joined forces to create Women of Liberia Mass Action for Peace. They wore white, to symbolize peace. They staged silent non-violent protests and forced a meeting with President Charles Taylor, and made him promise to attend peace talks in Ghana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, two Liberian women went to Ghana to continue to apply pressure on the warring factions during the peace process. They gathered up Liberian women refugees living in Ghana, and they staged a sit-in outside the Presidential Palace, blocking all the doors and windows and preventing anyone from leaving the peace talks without a resolution. They became a political force against violence and against their government. Their actions brought about an agreement during the stalled peace talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the women were able to achieve peace in Liberia after a 16 years of civil war and later helped bring to power the country’s first female head of state, Ellen Johnson Sirleaf. They developed networks which, properly utilised, could form an effective basis for that community development which is fundamental to peace. They worked incessantly and with great courage, in many cases against terrible odds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was Special Envoy for UNSCR 1325 we held three major conferences involving women who had survived conflict in Timor Leste, Liberia and Ireland. The first in Belfast was on &lt;strong&gt;“The Participation of Women”&lt;/strong&gt; in electoral politics, community and local government. The second conference theme in Dili addressed &lt;strong&gt;“The Protection of Women”&lt;/strong&gt;: issues of health, justice and security. The third conference in Monrovia addressed the context of UNSCR 1325: mediation, post-conflict recovery and transitional justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusions of the three conferences, each of which was preceded by preliminary work were very practical, reflecting the reality of the life of women caught in conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Vitally important is education, but it is so difficult for the girls to get to school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of Women’s Participation they were very clear for example that completion of schooling for girls, and access to formal and informal education for women are essential to generating confidence and the capacity to enter leadership roles. The one thing the women from these countries know to be vitally important is education, but it is so difficult for the girls to get to school. One father said to me one day, &lt;strong&gt;“why should I send her to school? She is a girl.”&lt;/strong&gt; That was very common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Targets and quotas for involvement actually work – they are not negative or ‘tokenistic’ but are a key strategy;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support structures for elected women such as a Women’s Caucus are useful;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Gender Champions’ in Government and Gender Action Plans can work;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resources need to be brought down to local level and communication must go from the grass roots to national levels;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Men have to be involved all the way and may need to be convinced of the importance of female involvement;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Family-friendly working arrangements are necessary in order for women to participate fully in decision making roles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the protection of women the conclusions were wide ranging:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That working with wide-ranging ‘social guardians’ such as churches to disseminate messages on GBV has worked;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That there has to be local access to medical help and trauma counselling and other help when a woman has experienced violence. This help very often comes from women themselves on the ground building up such services as they can;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There need to be more opportunities for women in the security sector.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conference 3 (How to Incorporate the Gender Perspective in Governance) was in some ways more difficult. The women were very specific though:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They need constantly and consistently to establish specific strategies to ensure women’s concerns are addressed. Otherwise they are excluded.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Women’s centres to provide an important space to collectively organise;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Institutional and legislative reforms to allow women to own property, and deal with issues such as rape and domestic violence;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance that women can act as mediators: they will focus on what they want for their children and grandchildren;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Women are often able to pre-empt the potential for violence because they know their communities and the dynamics within the communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the three years during which I was Ireland’s Special Envoy to Timor Leste and for the UN Resolutions on Women, Peace and Security my work took me all over the world, working with women in wars and conflict situations and I saw just how much women can achieve even when everything seems to be against them. This is what the children of Timor Leste said, when they were living in UNHCR camps without water or electricity during the war:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We want to go back home”;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We don’t want to sleep on ground covered with dew”;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We want to go to school because we are the nation’s future”;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We want to play in peace”;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We don’t want to hear the sound of guns”;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We don’t want to see blood spilling in our homes and our neighbours’ homes”;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“We don’t want to see our homes or our neighbours’ homes burnt down”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I want to just say a word about some wonderful young girls whom I met in the Gaza Camp Girls School in Jordan on 11 November, 2013. They were members of the school parliament. It was a long drive from Amman in Jordan across the mountains until we arrived at the camp, perched on the side of a barren mountain. It has been there since the people fled from Gaza in 1967 and were located there, not recognised as refugees. They are displaced people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only people who bring them help are UNWRA, established in 1967 to care for the Palestinian people in exile. UNWRA appear to have very limited resources. In 40+ years they have not been able to achieve as much as the UNHCR have achieved at Zatary Camp, Jordan in just over a year. They cannot go back to Gaza. They have no identity, no right to work in the public service, no homeland, no ability to travel and experience the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If they win a place there are two hurdles to overcome. In the first instance their fathers must allow them to go.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girls embroider beautiful pictures in Arabic text, some saying I love Palestine, the place they have never seen. They dream of a future filled with hope, of careers and travel, but their families have been effectively imprisoned in this place for forty years. There is very little way out. They have no money to go anywhere else. There are over 5000 children in the school. They are educated but the state allocates only 29 places at university for these children and if they win a place there are two hurdles to overcome. In the first instance their fathers must allow them to go. Secondly they are required to pay international fees which are prohibitively expensive and not manageable for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men can give their daughters so very little and their tradition is that the girls will be married very young and will then be involved in a life of caring for others, with no respite and no change. Learning is their lives at the present moment. They are dedicated to learning. Their teachers, despite the difficulties, are educating them. Many of them can speak English. Some of them told us about how they write, one writes poetry. They have access, though sometimes very limited, to the web, and to the world through the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do they want, these beautiful, bright, articulate, talented young women, living out their young lives on the bleak mountain side? They told us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They want to be recognised as human beings with rights, not as people with no identity who are helpless;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They want the right to own property;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They want not to be poor, to be able to work;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They want something to do outside school hours, other than the monotonous drudgery of housework;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They do not want to see so many relatives sitting at home useless, unable to do anything. They do not want to be useless too;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They want a good education. If they are unable to go to college or university because of the barriers put in their way, they will do other things. They will write and do all they can to study;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Several of them want to study medicine. One wants to be a cinematic director;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If they cannot study then they want to learn;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They do not want to be forced into early marriages;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They do not want to become pregnant in their early teens after a forced marriage;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They want to be happy. &lt;strong&gt;“Everything is about grieving”&lt;/strong&gt;, one said, &lt;strong&gt;“even when it seems there might be some happiness, it always ends in sadness for all that has been lost.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Above all they want to be able to make a contribution to the world they live using their talents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am trying now to find some way of bringing some contact with the outside world to these girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must be patient working for peace. There are so many young women in terrible circumstances. The work which you do does make a difference. We should never give up, no matter what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish you all every success and every happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://nualaoloan.com//conflict-resolution/soroptimists-international-charter-lunch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://nualaoloan.com//conflict-resolution/soroptimists-international-charter-lunch/</guid>
        
        
        <category>conflict-resolution</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
